<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>JBake</title>
    <link>http://azuaron.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://azuaron.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <description>JBake Bootstrap Template</description>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 15:40:50 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 15:40:50 -0400</lastBuildDate>

    <item>
      <title>Travis CI and Codecov</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2016/01/travis-ci-and-codecov.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2016/01/travis-ci-and-codecov.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I ended up at OpenShift because I was looking for a free Jenkins solution, Jenkins being the CI tool with which I&amp;#39;m most familiar. But, I&amp;#39;ve since discovered &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://travis-ci.org/Azuaron/wp2jbake&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Travis CI&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, which is incredibly open-source friendly and perfect for this plugin project. Along with that, I discovered &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://codecov.io/github/Azuaron/wp2jbake?ref=master&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Codecov&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; which stores code coverage statistics (calculated with &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://eclemma.org/jacoco/trunk/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Jacoco&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;). With both of these up and running, there&amp;#39;s no need for the Jenkins solution on OpenShift.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;So, what to do with OpenShift? With all three gears open, I can get a SonarQube instance running (one gear for the server, one gear for the unused scalable web front, and one gear for the database). That being said, having Travis and Codecov running significantly reduces the need to get that running, so it&amp;#39;s been put on the back burner for the moment.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: The Dark Tower by Stephen King</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/12/dark-tower_stephen-king.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/12/dark-tower_stephen-king.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://amzn.to/1YR3l5n&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Light spoilers for the whole series above, deep spoilers near the end (another warning will be issue).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I am not one of Stephen King&amp;#39;s Constant Readers. I picked up &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Gunslinger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; in a Barnes &amp;amp;amp; Noble on a whim and fell in love with the first line: &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The man in Black fled across the Desert, and the Gunslinger followed.&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; In the subsequent days, I fell in love with the entire book. To my disappointment, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Gunslinger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is the peak of the series.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There have been high points (*&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/08/wolves-calla-stephen-king/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;The Wolves of the Calla&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;*) and particularly low points (*The Waste Lands*) but the series could never match the brutal, elegant, beautiful simplicity of that first book.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And finally, we get to the core of it: The Dark Tower has never been about anything other than Stephen King. He claims to hate the word &amp;quot;metafiction&amp;quot; (which means an author has inserted themself into their book), but he drags the whole series through what is, ultimately, a metafictional narrative and nothing else. The Dark Tower series exists for one reason and one reason alone: to tie together the collective, varied works of Stephen King. Not only that, but he inserts himself into the story as, basically, the prophet of our Lord and Savior Gan, Keeper of the Dark Tower. A fascinating look into the mind of Stephen King? Yes. An engaging story? Not really. The final body blow after you realize you&amp;#39;ve wasted years of your life reading a story about other stories you haven&amp;#39;t read? King literally becomes his own deus ex machina... &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;then &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/LampshadeHanging&amp;quot;&amp;gt;lampshades&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; it&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Deep spoilers to follow. You&amp;#39;ve been warned.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Dark Tower&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; ends twice, one of which I kind of liked, the other I really didn&amp;#39;t. Let&amp;#39;s talk about the one I liked first.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;What Roland finds at the top of the Dark Tower is... a return to the desert first seen in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Gunslinger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, and the beginning of his journey once again. As we&amp;#39;ve been told oh so many times, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;ka&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is a wheel, so a return to the beginning should not surprise anyone. As a reader of Stephen King, an ending that&amp;#39;s more than slightly horrific for the protagonist shouldn&amp;#39;t surprise anyone, either. Honestly, there&amp;#39;s nothing else that should be at the top of the tower.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;What Susannah finds in New York, on the other hand, is a cop out. Eddie, Jake, and Oy sacrificed themselves for the mission, for &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;ka&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, for each other, and for Roland. To find them strolling around New York City in some alternate &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;where&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; so Susannah can find them diminishes their sacrifices. It makes sense, I guess, and it doesn&amp;#39;t break any rules of the world... but 11th hour resurrections are always the wrong decision. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Always&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. It takes a clear-cut cause and effect chain and says, &amp;quot;Gotcha! Different effect! Surprise happy ending!&amp;quot; Oh, they don&amp;#39;t live happily ever after, they merely live and have happiness? That&amp;#39;s a lot different; thanks, I feel better about your cop out now &amp;lt;/sarcasm&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;On it&amp;#39;s own, I&amp;#39;d give the book &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Dark Tower&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; 3 roses out of 5. As a stand-in for the series as a whole, I&amp;#39;d give it 2. Knowing what I know now, I would read &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Gunslinger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and stop there.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Wordpress to JBake content conversion tool</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/12/wordpress-to-jbake-content-conversion-tool.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/12/wordpress-to-jbake-content-conversion-tool.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Over the Christmas break, I&amp;#39;ve been coding up a tool to convert all my Wordpress posts into JBake content. The idea is that it would take a Wordpress Export file and turn it into the content and assets folders in JBake. Since I&amp;#39;ve got my JBake instance running in Gradle, I&amp;#39;m writing this as a Gradle plugin. That being said, I&amp;#39;m not entirely comfortable with Groovy, so there&amp;#39;s only a small Groovy shim between the Gradle build and the main application, which is pure Java. If this plugin gets some traction with other people, I&amp;#39;ll write a similar shim for a Maven plugin.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The plugin&amp;#39;s called wp2jbake and I&amp;#39;ve open-sourced the code (GPL2). It can be &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://github.com/Azuaron/wp2jbake&amp;quot;&amp;gt;found on GitHub here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The most difficult part of all this, oddly enough, has been trying to setup Jenkins and Sonar on &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://www.openshift.com/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;OpenShift&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. OpenShift is a cloud-based PaaS product from RedHat, and they give you 3 small gears for free (which seems perfect for a small, opensource CI platform). I ran into two primary problems. First, I&amp;#39;m not an ops guy, so every step of this is a painstaking example of how not to go about setting these things up. More importantly, it turns out it&amp;#39;s impossible within OpenShift to setup what I&amp;#39;m looking for without going over the 3 gear limit.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;quot;You&amp;#39;re going over the 3 gear limit,&amp;quot; some of the more informed of you are saying. &amp;quot;But it sounds like you only need two gears, one for Jenkins and one for Sonar. Three, max, if the database is on its own gear.&amp;quot; Which is exactly what I thought, but I ran into certain problems specific to OpenShift&amp;#39;s restrictions.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;First, we have to talk about how OpenShift handles applications. When you create an application, first you need a &amp;quot;web&amp;quot; application to handle web requests. This can be something basic like a Tomcat or PHP instance, or something more complete like Jenkins. You can then add to this web application additional &amp;quot;cartridges,&amp;quot; things like databases or certain clients that don&amp;#39;t require inbound web requests. You can&amp;#39;t have more than one web cartridge in an application.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;OpenShift also has a concept of &amp;quot;scalable&amp;quot;. When you create a web application, you can make it scalable, which means it can dynamically spin up instances of itself on additional gears (if your account has them open). There are certain exceptions to this; Jenkins, for instance, can&amp;#39;t be scalable because it shares file resources. Similarly, the &amp;quot;DIY&amp;quot; cartridge which I was using to install Sonar could not be made scalable for the same reason. Sonar, however, requires a database instance (unless you&amp;#39;re using the embedded H2 instance, but then what&amp;#39;s the point? If it restarts, you&amp;#39;ll lose your data.)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Sonar also requires this database instance to be accessible to both the client and the server, our client in this case being our Jenkins instance. The Jenkins and DIY cartridges are both web cartridges, so they must be different applications. But to be externally accessible, the database has to sit on its own gear, either in one of these applications or on a different one. Neither Jenkins nor DIY can be made scalable, which means the database can&amp;#39;t be a cartridge on either of them. A database is not a web cartridge, so it can&amp;#39;t sit as its own application. So, to get around this, I could make a different app scalable (PHP or NodeJS or something) and just ignore the web part of that. Problem solved, right? Except count the gears:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;1 - Jenkins application&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;1 - DIY Sonar application&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;2 - Database application (1 for the web app that I&amp;#39;m not even using and 1 for the database)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Is there a way around this? Not right now. There&amp;#39;s been a feature request for at least two years to make a scalable DIY cartridge, but it hasn&amp;#39;t happened yet. It seems strange to me that you can&amp;#39;t spin up a solitary gear with a database, but there you go.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;So, right now I do have a Jenkins server up and running and polling from &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://github.com/Azuaron/wp2jbake&amp;quot;&amp;gt;GitHub&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; every hour, but I&amp;#39;m going to have to setup a local SonarQube instance until/if I find a better solution.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Switching from Wordpress.com to JBake on GitHub pages</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/12/switching-from-wordpress-com-to-jbake-on-github-pages.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/12/switching-from-wordpress-com-to-jbake-on-github-pages.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In an effort to cut costs, I recently migrated from a hosted site to Wordpress.com. Wordpress.com&amp;#39;s about a tenth the price of a hosted solution, but comes with some pretty significant caveats (the biggest being their &amp;quot;no plugins&amp;quot; rule). As a programmer, not having plugins essentially hamstrings my ability to fiddle with the site, something I&amp;#39;m wont to do every few months.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I&amp;#39;ve also been investigating static site generators, which have intrigued me for a while. Compared to dynamic sites, a static site is blazing fast (since no calculations need to be performed, it just serves the pages), but they also come with some caveats (no dynamic content). At first glance, it seems like having a static site has more in common with having a Geocities site in the 90s than having a modern website.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But Javascript has come a long way since then, and comments (and other systems) can now work via services like &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://disqus.com/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Disqus&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; which use Javascript, thus allowing dynamic content on a static site.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;With that in mind, I&amp;#39;m going to convert this website to a &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://jbake.org&amp;quot;&amp;gt;JBake&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; site (JBake is a Java-based static site generator) hosted on GitHub (for free--thank you GitHub!) The WiP site can be found &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, the generated code for which can be found &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://github.com/Azuaron/azuaron.github.io&amp;quot;&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. Finally, the JBake code can be found &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://github.com/Azuaron/forest-azuaron-jbake&amp;quot;&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I hope to document this process as it comes along. So far, I&amp;#39;ve got JBake building using Markdown and Thymeleaf on Gradle using &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://melix.github.io/blog/2014/02/hosting-jbake-github.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;this guy&amp;#39;s&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; tutorial and plugins. That post&amp;#39;s a little out of date, so if you want to follow in my footsteps you may want to look through the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://github.com/Azuaron/forest-azuaron-jbake&amp;quot;&amp;gt;JBake code&amp;#39;s Gradle files&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. I&amp;#39;ve licensed all the code under the GPLv2.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;My next step&amp;#39;s going to be to export all my posts, images, tags, etc. from Wordpress.com then convert all that into JBake content in Markdown. I hope to create a JBake or Gradle plugin for this process, so other people can as well.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>It Follows</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/12/it-follows.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 9 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/12/it-follows.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://amzn.to/1HTLS4D&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Trigger warning for sex crimes involving children.&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The Good&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The monster in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;It Follows&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is an intriguing concept; it somehow distills the standard slasher villain into it&amp;#39;s most basic components while still feeling entirely new.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The monster is invisible to everyone other than its victims and can, itself, look like anyone. This combination breeds a special brand of paranoia into its victims, since nothing they see can be verified by anyone else &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;and&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; their stalker can be &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;literally anyone they see&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;True to its name, it follows. No matter where you go, it will walk directly toward you. The key word is walk; it&amp;#39;s not very fast. You can drive or fly, but it always knows where you are, and will always walk straight toward you. It can&amp;#39;t be fooled and, given its super strength, it can&amp;#39;t be stopped. Well, I would have actually liked a bit more explanation into this. Like, if you tricked it into jumping into a large pit, then filled that pit with quick drying cement, can it get out of that? How about molten lead? A fair few questions remain outside the scope of the movie. From a more practical standpoint, if you flew to Europe, could it cross the ocean? It seems like this should have been their first plan, but no one tried more than &amp;quot;drive an hour away&amp;quot;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The Bad&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Now that we&amp;#39;re post-&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://amzn.to/1HTMyHi&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cabin In The Woods&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, can we stop using the standard set of protagonists? It&amp;#39;s boring. Yes, your &amp;quot;virgin&amp;quot; archetype isn&amp;#39;t really a virgin, but she&amp;#39;s still the archetype. Oh, your &amp;quot;jock&amp;quot; doesn&amp;#39;t actually play sports and is the &amp;quot;bad boy&amp;quot; of the school? The smart guy is also the stoner? Please try harder, or, even, at all.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;After the core group gets &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://youtu.be/B_WNViYEjzs?t=11m27s&amp;quot;&amp;gt;past the belief curve&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; everything plays out just about how you&amp;#39;d expect; the only surprises are the unintentionally uncomfortable ones (detailed below).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The Ugly (spoilers ahead)&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;How this monster chooses its targets is, well, presumably there was a &amp;quot;patient zero&amp;quot; at one point, we don&amp;#39;t know how this thing got started. But it can be transferred to another person by having sex with them. That&amp;#39;s right, this is the monster-personification of an STI. The only problem is, transferring it to someone makes it stop coming after you. So, essentially, this monster works via the &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;real world, pervasive, and dangerous myth&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; that has sprung up many times around the world: having sex will cure you of your infection. Usually, the myth says it&amp;#39;s sex with virgins, which typically means people are raping children to &amp;quot;cure&amp;quot; themselves of the disease. Not only does this fail spectacularly by &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;not&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; curing the infection, but it also &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;spreads the infection&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and, oh yes, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;children were raped&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This happened with syphilis in Europe. It&amp;#39;s happening right now with HIV in Africa.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I can&amp;#39;t tell if the writers were aware of this, or just bumbled into it, but either way it&amp;#39;s pretty disgusting that this movie re-enforces the myth that having sex with someone will cure your &amp;quot;infection&amp;quot;. It seems like this is probably unintentional; going along with the theme of &amp;quot;distilling the classic slasher villain&amp;quot;, then sex has to have negative consequences (because for some reason that trope hasn&amp;#39;t died). But this is just gross in all the wrong ways.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Spoiler Review: Beyond the Shadows by Brent Weeks</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/07/spoiler-review-beyond-the-shadows-by-brent-weeks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/07/spoiler-review-beyond-the-shadows-by-brent-weeks.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesbeyond-shadows_weeks-186x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Beyond the Shadows by Brent Weeks&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001KNVP0K/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001KNVP0K&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=ZUIVW2G4ACVM35YE&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Spoilers!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The first two books of the Night Angel trilogy I classify as very good popcorn books: incredibly readable, but not a lot else. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Beyond the Shadows&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, however, transcends popcorn book status and becomes something legitimately great, and I&amp;#39;d like to talk about why, and I can&amp;#39;t without spoilage.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The greatest achievement of the book, I believe, is its transformation from grim-dark to epic fantasy. The first book opens with child rape, and the third book ends with the ushering in of a new era brought about by &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;the literal power of love&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. I find that to be an incredibly stunning transforming. Imagine if &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Song of Ice and Fire&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; ended like that, especially since Martin has threatened to kill &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;literally everyone&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Winds of Winter&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and write 1000 pages of wind blowing across a blasted snowscape for &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;A Dream of Spring&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And, more astonishingly, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;it works&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Sure, the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;ka&amp;#39;kari&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is a creature/being/magic/thing of destruction powered by love, but it&amp;#39;s powered by love by &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;murdering those you love&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, which makes metaphysical sense and has absolutely devastating consequences. Sure, Elene&amp;#39;s selfless love for Kylar and humanity is the fulcrum which allows them to defeat Khali, but comes at the cost of her death.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Some things that were weird or could have gone better:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Kylar had Curoch. And Lantano had the Curoch forgery. Both were at the final battle. And... Lantano just happened to never be near the other Curoch? That just seems like a missed opportunity.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Kylar got &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;both&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; girls in the love triangle. Many spouses are of the opinion that, should they die, their significant other should move on and find someone else. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Not&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; many spouses choose that &amp;quot;someone else&amp;quot; ahead of time.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Neph Dada spends a lot of time and effort resurrecting that Titan. And Kylar kills it in twenty seconds. And ten minutes later, there were a whole bunch of Titans all over the place. There was a lot of build up for this one creature, and not very much pay off.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;I suppose it will probably come up in later books, but The Strangers plot-line never really went anywhere.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Being a great healer allows you to teleport a fetus into another womb?&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Martian by Andy Weir</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/07/martian-weir.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/07/martian-weir.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesmartian_weir-182x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Martian by Andy Weir&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553418025/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0553418025&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=VIY2S5B74UVPWNZC&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Martian&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; by Andy Weir is the best hard science fiction I&amp;#39;ve ever read (disclaimer: I haven&amp;#39;t read a lot of hard science fiction). Simultaneously hilarious, nail-biting, and heroic while being scientifically accurate (the final print version, at least). And, since it&amp;#39;s science fiction in the very-near-future, there&amp;#39;s little-to-no hand-waving; the technology in the book is technology we have and understand &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;today&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Most impressively, the plot is not driven by a need to move from one set-piece disaster to another--as is the case with most Man vs Nature stories. Instead, the plot is driven by the science, the probable outcomes that naturally arise from being stranded on Mars, and the direct consequences of previous actions. In other words, at no point during the novel did I have the thought, &amp;quot;And now for the obligatory &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;X&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;!&amp;quot; (A statement I utter with increasing frequency as I read more and more books.) Finally, though both the frame (recording logs to be found later) and through the engaging personality of our hero Matt Damon Mark Watney, Weir manages to keep the book engaging even though it is, at its core, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://xkcd.com/1536/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;about taking a table full of parts and connecting this thing to this thing&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The characters are a bit thin, and everything ultimately shakes out exactly as you think it will, but it&amp;#39;s a Hell of ride.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 Pathfinders out of 5; would get stranded on the Red Planet again.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;1 – Nearly incomprehensible&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;2 – Can be read, but nothing to recommend it. Typos. Weak voice. Incoherent plot and characters. When people think of fan fiction, most of it’s about 2 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;3 – Technically competent. Readable. Unspectacular. The &amp;quot;popcorn movie&amp;quot; type of books tend to get 3 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 – Solidly good. New and interesting plot and characters and a strong voice. For me, the average Brandon Sanderson novel.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;5 – Mind blowing. I-read-it-in-one-sitting. Zero-to-no flaws.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>I Am Not A Serial Killer by Dan Wells</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/07/not-serial-killer-wells.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/07/not-serial-killer-wells.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesnot-serial-killer_wells-200x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;I Am Not A Serial Killer by Dan Wells&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765327821/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0765327821&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=INLUGAYHEHOSAKA7&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I read it in one day.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The clear point of comparison for &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;I Am Not A Serial Killer&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;/John Cleaver is to Dexter, so let&amp;#39;s start there. I like John better, as a character and a serial killer. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, I really enjoy Dexter (also read &amp;#39;em in a day), but I&amp;#39;ve never really been afraid of Dexter. Despite his total lack of empathy and tendency to murder, he blends in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;so well&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; that I would gladly be his friend. We could golf, have barbecues. The wives and kids playing in the back yard while we drink something manly and appropriate and make quips about bloody meat (or something). Dexter is so in control that, for a serial killer, he&amp;#39;s down-right cuddly.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;John Cleaver is not. He&amp;#39;s got his rules like Dexter, but Dexter&amp;#39;s rules are to keep Dexter out of jail, and John&amp;#39;s rules are to keep other people alive. And John just... can&amp;#39;t... stop... himself... &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;breaking&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; those rules. Whereas Dexter feels almost like &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Troll Hunter&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (from the excellent Norwegian film), a kind of &amp;quot;sanitation engineer&amp;quot; that removes monsters from society, John Cleaver feels like a &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;serial killer&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; who&amp;#39;s one bad day from &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;snapping and killing some random person&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Stepping away from John, for a moment, the conflict in the book arises from another serial killer in town who starts killing people, and John starts investigating him. Without going too far into it, this other killer is surprisingly sympathetic, which caught me off guard. In fact, at times, I&amp;#39;d say s/he&amp;#39;s more sympathetic than our hero protagonist. Which, honestly, adds even more to John&amp;#39;s inherent threatening nature and, I&amp;#39;d say, makes the book stronger.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The downside, well, some of it reads like a Wikipedia article about serial killers. It&amp;#39;s decently hid in dialog (for the most part), but the info-dumps are there. Luckily, I&amp;#39;m the kind of person who casually surfs Wikipedia for fun, so it wasn&amp;#39;t too bothersome.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 embalmings out of 5&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;1 – Nearly incomprehensible&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;2 – Can be read, but nothing to recommend it. Typos. Weak voice. Incoherent plot and characters. When people think of fan fiction, most of it’s about 2 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;3 – Technically competent. Readable. Unspectacular. The “popcorn movie” type of books tend to get 3 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 – Solidly good. New and interesting plot and characters and a strong voice. For me, the average Brandon Sanderson novel.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;5 – Mind blowing. I-read-it-in-one-sitting. Zero-to-no flaws.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Let&amp;#39;s talk about &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;IT&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, the reveal about 1/3 through the book. I knew about &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;IT&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; going in, and I think that&amp;#39;s the way to go. Very rarely is it beneficial for a reader to be surprised by the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;genre&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; that they&amp;#39;re reading (*Dexter in the Dark*, I&amp;#39;m looking at you). In fact, I can&amp;#39;t think of a single book that&amp;#39;s done it well. Imagine if &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;My Teacher is an Alien&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; were titled &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;I Don&amp;#39;t Like My Teacher&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, and then surprise! Aliens. I suspect very few people want that. Normally, I go far, far out of my way so I don&amp;#39;t reveal spoilers, but in this case I&amp;#39;m going to make an exception. But if you &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;do&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; want to be surprised, stop here.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;SPOILER ALERT&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A little bit of filler to hide wandering eyes and the competing killer&amp;#39;s a demon. I knew there were demons going in (thank you &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.writingexcuses.com/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Writing Excuses&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;) and the &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;, for me, was &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;who&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; the demon was more than &amp;quot;OMG WAT A DEMON&amp;quot;. Of course, I also had guessed who the killer was going to be as soon as they showed up. And as far as I&amp;#39;m concerned, all this demon business is perfectly okay. I mean, I&amp;#39;m also reading Stephen King, it&amp;#39;s not like the occasional demon&amp;#39;s going to break my suspension of disbelief--as long as I know that&amp;#39;s the genre I&amp;#39;m reading.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: The Bonehunters by Steven Erikson</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/07/bonehunters-erikson.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 4 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/07/bonehunters-erikson.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesThe_Bonehunters-179x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Bonehunters by Steven Erikson&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765348837/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0765348837&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=LOCJPLSAWPAHXKHG&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;It&amp;#39;s difficult for me to say too many good things about Steven Erikson&amp;#39;s Malazan series, and the books have been getting even better.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;It&amp;#39;s even more difficult, however, for me to say anything specific about why this book is so great, since even mentioning that a particular character is still alive (or not) at a particular point would be a serious spoiler, and I don&amp;#39;t believe the statute of limitations has quite run out on the Malazan series.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;What I can say, however, is that if you&amp;#39;ve made it &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;this&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; far, you will not be disappointed. While it doesn&amp;#39;t quite hit the emotional impact of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Midnight Tides&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, it continues Erikson&amp;#39;s evolution as an author, and the word-smithing&amp;#39;s better than ever. Where it falls down a little is the plot structure, which feels a little more fragmented than it needs to, right up until the last few hundred pages which are pure brilliance.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;5/5 shaved knuckles in the hole.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: Firefight by Brandon Sanderson</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/06/firefight-brandon-sanderson.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/06/firefight-brandon-sanderson.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesfirefight_sanderson-199x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Firefight by Brandon Sanderson&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0385743580/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0385743580&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=7DFUIEPNKFVBBKJQ&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Firefight&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is a serviceable sequel to the amazing &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Steelheart&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. We get a bit more of an understanding of the Epics and their powers, particularly where their powers come from... and not much else. David is David, Prof is Prof, Val is Val, and we&amp;#39;ve got some new characters to pad out the roster, but it all feels like filler, like it should have been shortened and used as the opening to &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Calamity&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Of course, having read all Sanderson&amp;#39;s published works, it&amp;#39;s entirely possible I&amp;#39;m just spoiled. It&amp;#39;s still &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Sanderson&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, so it&amp;#39;s still exciting and well-crafted. I just expect &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;more&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; from him at this point.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 fortune cookies out of 5&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Metal songs for fantasy authors and their worlds</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/05/metal-songs-fantasy-authors-worlds.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/05/metal-songs-fantasy-authors-worlds.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I read &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.tor.com/2015/05/27/metal-music-for-five-fantasy-writers-and-their-worlds/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;this post on Tor about matching fantasy authors and their worlds with metal songs&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and now I&amp;#39;m highly motivated to write while listening to some metal.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>You Pick Videogame Marathon for Charity</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/05/you-pick-videogame-marathon-for-charity.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/05/you-pick-videogame-marathon-for-charity.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I have a friend from college (&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.twitter.com/stephonee&amp;quot;&amp;gt;@stephonee&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;) who runs a yearly charity event for &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://www.charitywater.org/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;charity: water&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;*. This event takes the form of a ridiculous videogame marathon where the givers choose the games and how long they&amp;#39;re played by their donations. It is ridiculous in that it&amp;#39;s 48-straight hours and the chosen games aren&amp;#39;t, shall we say, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;necessarily fun to play&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (Battletoads and the infamous Desert Bus are often in the list of contenders).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This event is called &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.upickvg.com/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;UPickVG IV&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and it starts on June 12th!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;*Charity for getting clean water to people in impoverished nations without clean water.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: The Last Continent by Terry Pratchett</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/05/last-continent-terry-pratchett.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/05/last-continent-terry-pratchett.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imageslast-continent_pratchett-193x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Last Continent by Terry Pratchett&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0062280198/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0062280198&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=UHVBF3QO6LGNM3CM&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I&amp;#39;ve never liked Rincewind. He&amp;#39;s got all the likability of a sea mine, and about as much directionless destructive ability. This is the point, I suppose, and while I don&amp;#39;t necessarily need a likable lead to like a novel (certain Malazan books come to mind), there&amp;#39;s a detestability about Rincewind that makes me want to obsessively wash my hands.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The wizards of Unseen University occupy a similar space in my brain, with the possible exception of Ponder Stibbons and the Bursar (but only by comparison to the other wizards).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;quot;But was it &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;funny?&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;quot; I hear people ask in some dark corner of my brain desperate to anticipate the questions of others and answer them preemptively. Well, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;yes&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, it&amp;#39;s still Pratchett, even if it&amp;#39;s weakened by the wizzards. But it&amp;#39;s popcorn-movie funny, in a way I won&amp;#39;t remember two months from now. With the possible exception of the Mad Max bit, which was oddly fitting given that &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Fury Road&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; comes out &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;today&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;3 armored unicycles out of a blasted wasteland full of poisonous spiders.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: Stranger in a Strange Land by Robert Heinlein</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/05/stranger-strange-land-heinlein.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/05/stranger-strange-land-heinlein.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2015/05/stranger_heinlein.jpg&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesstranger_heinlein-180x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Stranger in a Strange Land by Robert Heinlein&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0441790348/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0441790348&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=EKESYDPPON5KVHFX&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Stranger in a Strange Land, in two parts. 1: The Obligatory What Does the Government Do. 2: The Philosophy of Sexual Politics according to Robert Heinlein.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Part 1 is quite good, and you can see how it will later become the foundation for many &amp;quot;lone special person baffles government officials&amp;quot; stories for decades to come--though I do wonder how much &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Stranger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; was influenced by &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Day the Earth Stood Still&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Unfortunately, it feels a little rushed. Like, Heinlein really wanted to write Part 2, but knew he couldn&amp;#39;t get away with it without addressing Part 1.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Part 2, well, let&amp;#39;s just say you may not want to talk sexual philosophy with the same book that brings us such wonderful quotes as, &amp;quot;9 times out of 10, when a woman is raped, it&amp;#39;s her fault,&amp;quot; and, &amp;quot;This isn&amp;#39;t one of those times when women have the vote!&amp;quot; Also, you&amp;#39;ll never understand the philosophy, anyway, unless you learn to think in Martian. Thanks Heinlein for clearing up everything! Thou art God!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A single 3.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Edit: Ugh, I&amp;#39;ve just found out there&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;cut&amp;quot; (the original publication) and &amp;quot;uncut&amp;quot; (published in the 90s) versions of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Stranger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, and I read the cut version. I am not interested enough to try it again, but it&amp;#39;s likely that colored my experience.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: The Currents of Space by Isaac Asimov</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/04/currents-space-isaac-asimov.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/04/currents-space-isaac-asimov.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765319179/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0765319179&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=FRDFBL24KQA7NHXM&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagescurrents-space_asimov-200x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Currents of Space by Isaac Asimov&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765319179/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0765319179&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=FRDFBL24KQA7NHXM&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Depending on your point of view, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Currents of Space&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is either the last, second, or first book in the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Galactic Empire&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; trilogy: it was published last, but the depicted events happen before &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Pebble in the Sky&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and after &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Stars, Like Dust&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, but is recommended as the first to read by &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www3.sympatico.ca/n.rieck/links/cool_sci_fi.html#asimov-suggested-reading-order&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Asimov himself&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. Personally, I find I can&amp;#39;t read things out of in-universe chronological order, so &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Currents of Space&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is my second foray into &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Galactic Empire&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, following &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Stars, Like Dust&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;While I found &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Stars, Like Dust&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; to be merely good, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Currents of Space&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is now my favorite Asimov book.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Let&amp;#39;s talk about the &amp;quot;main character has amnesia&amp;quot; plot, and how well Asimov side-stepped what makes that so clichéd anymore. First, while Rik is certainly the most important character in the book and drives the plot forward, most of our time is not spent with him. We spend most of our time with people like the Townman and Dr. Junz, and Rik is merely &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;around&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Second, Rik is not &amp;quot;basically himself, but without his memories&amp;quot; or even &amp;quot;used to be a bad guy, but now is without his memories and naive&amp;quot;. The process by which his memories are lost has had a catastrophic effect on Rik, and when he is first found he has the mental capacity of an infant. Finally, the plot isn&amp;#39;t about making Rik remember. Remembering is something that happens during the plot, but no one sits around showing him things saying, &amp;quot;How about this? Does this trigger anything?&amp;quot; Sixty years later, and Asimov&amp;#39;s handling of the amnesia plot feels fresher than anything in the past decade.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Then there&amp;#39;s the plot itself. While the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Robots&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; series might be the explicit detective novels, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Currents of Space&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is, in my opinion, a better-crafted mystery than any of them. So well-crafted, in fact, that I hesitate to say anything about it for fear of spoiling, despite it being 60 years old and well passed the statute of limitations on spoiling.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Finally, I really enjoyed the characters. One of the primary problems I had with the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Robots&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; series was that everyone was, essentially, some academic or another and spoke appropriately, so there was no range of voices. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Currents of Space&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is the first of Asimov&amp;#39;s books I&amp;#39;ve read that really shows his skill with dialog, and his ability to get inside the heads of a broad range of characters.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;5 carbon atoms out of a supernova.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Further thoughts:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Could the titles of the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Galactic Empire&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; trilogy be any more beautiful?&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;I really need to accelerate my frequency of reading Asmov novels. 8 years since I started, and I still haven&amp;#39;t gotten to &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Foundation&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;I find it somewhat inappropriately humorous that everyone on Earth is basically Simon Pegg in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;A Fantastic Fear of Everything&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: 1634: The Ram Rebellion by Eric Flint and Virginia DeMarce</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/04/ram-rebellion-flint-demarce.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/04/ram-rebellion-flint-demarce.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesram-rebellion_flint-demarce-199x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Ram Rebellion by Eric Flint and Virginia DeMarce&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1416573828/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1416573828&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=KXPVDAWULWXFA72M&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The most important thing to know about &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Ram Rebellion&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is that it isn&amp;#39;t a novel, but a series of short stories on the same topic (The Ram Rebellion) that culminate into a novella, and these shorts are not written by the same authors. The result is that the story quality is incredibly uneven; some are quite good, and some are quite bad.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The second most important thing to know is that the rebellion doesn&amp;#39;t actually occur until half-way through the ending novella; or, to put it another way, 600 pages into a 700 page mass market paperback.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;To be perfectly upfront, I&amp;#39;m not a short story guy. If they&amp;#39;re good, then I would have liked to spend more time with them. If they&amp;#39;re bad, well, then they&amp;#39;re bad. Which makes my interest in the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Ring of Fire&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; series unfortunate, since they are more short stories far outnumber the novels--I&amp;#39;ve lost count of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Grantville Gazettes&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Ring of Fire&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; anthologies that have been published. Then, to open up what I expected to be a novel and find short stories instead...&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Now that I&amp;#39;ve exposed my own biases, let&amp;#39;s move on to actually reviewing the book. It&amp;#39;s divided into four parts (three sets of shorts, followed by the novella), so I&amp;#39;ll divide my review accordingly.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Part One: Recipes for Revolution&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There&amp;#39;s two stories of note in this part: &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Birdie&amp;#39;s Farm&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Birdie&amp;#39;s Village&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, both by Gorg Huff and Paula Goodlett. The other three (all by Eric Flint) are connective tissue that tie the stories into the larger context of Grantville and the Ram Rebellion. The Birdie stories are pretty good, and provide important context for the rebellion, assuming you&amp;#39;re interested in 17th century property ownership, tenantship, and legal minutia, which I am, but I assume I&amp;#39;m in the minority on that.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Part Two: Enter the Ram&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The first three stories, all by some combination of Paula Goodlett, Virginia DeMarce, Stanley Leghorn, Rick Boatright, Kerryn Offord, and Laura Runkle, deal with the eponymous ram, which at this stage of the story is a literal ram. While I understand where they ultimately went with it, and the symbology that grew out of the ram, the stories about the ram are a dull slog.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The fourth and final story (*A Night at the Ballet* by Kerryn Offord) might be interesting to ballet aficionados, particularly if they like reading stories written from a first-person perspective that&amp;#39;s devoid of all character. All in all, I wish I&amp;#39;d skipped part 2; I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;d have missed anything.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Part Three: The Trouble in Franconia&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Finally, we get to the region where a rebellion will occur. There&amp;#39;s a lot less cohesion across stories than there is in Parts 1 and 2, but not to the detriment of the whole. If I were to read this book again, I&amp;#39;d probably just read parts 3 and 4, and be happier for it, since this is where we finally get to the root causes and reactions for and against the rebellion. In particular, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Suhl Incident&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; by Eric Flint and John Zeek is probably the best story in the book, a smart combination of political maneuvering and hard action.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Part Four: The Ram Rebellion&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Finally, we get to the rebellion! Apparently. Wait, when&amp;#39;s this rebellion start? Apparently not for another hundred pages. A few things become clear upon reading part four.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;First, that the novella was written independently of the rest of the stories; it stands complete, and can, therefore, be read independently of the rest without losing much.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Second, since it&amp;#39;s independent and comes at the &amp;quot;end&amp;quot; of the book, none of the rest of the stories can actually be about the rebellion, but must remain as part of the build-up to the rebellion. This is, quite simply, poor story structure. For quite obvious reasons, the build-up of a story usually shouldn&amp;#39;t take more than the first third. If it takes longer, it not only drags on beyond the reader&amp;#39;s interest, but forces the compression of the action and pay off, thus reducing their impact.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Third, since it stands complete, the first half is dedicated to, you guessed it, more build-up. Which, if you&amp;#39;re reading &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;just&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Ram Rebellion&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, is probably a good thing. But if you&amp;#39;ve just read the previous 500 pages only to come to the end and get &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;even more&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; build-up...&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Overall&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I can&amp;#39;t recommend &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Ram Rebellion&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Several of the stories are just plain bad, and even the good ones are stuck amidst a disappointing overall arc. 2 Merino rams out of 5.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: Absolute Sandman, Vol. 4 by Neil Gaiman</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/absolute-sandman-4-neil-gaiman.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/absolute-sandman-4-neil-gaiman.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagessandman-ng-212x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Absolute Sandman, Vol. 4 by Neil Gaiman&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1401210856/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1401210856&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=S5CPGYWBRYBPBRNB&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;To understand this review, first you have to understand how I read the Sandman comics. Whenever my wife goes away for a few days, I read a volume of the Absolute Sandman. I don&amp;#39;t quite know how I started this or why, but this is how things are. And, just over a year ago, my daughter was born. The past several days have been the first my daughter&amp;#39;s been away from me since she was born.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This is the environment in which I&amp;#39;ve started--and finished--*Absolute Sandman, Vol 4*. For reasons that will become obvious, spoilers to follow.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The arcs in Vol 4 are &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Kindly Ones&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Wake&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Or, to put it another way, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Death of Dream&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and, well, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Wake&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. What a positively depressing way to spend my depressing weekend away from my family. But, quite possibly the most beautiful story ever written. This is Gaiman at his best: the opposition of two unstoppable powers, very little &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;combat&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; in favor of deep &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;conflict&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, sacrifice, grace, and transformation. I wasn&amp;#39;t a fan of the art style for &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Kindly Ones&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (seemed too cartoony), but it didn&amp;#39;t distract and I particularly liked &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Wake&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;#39;s art.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>New Series: First to Review</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/new-series-first-to-review.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/new-series-first-to-review.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Nothing kills a book on Amazon&amp;#39;s Kindle marketplace like having no reviews. Though I can&amp;#39;t find any at this particular moment (#Googlefail), I&amp;#39;ve read several articles that say even &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;bad&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; reviews are better than &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;no&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; reviews.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Keeping that in mind, and being in a &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://smile.amazon.com/Letters-Old-God-Earth-Book-ebook/dp/B00IC864OI&amp;quot;&amp;gt;similar boat&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; myself, I plan to periodically find a book for Kindle without any reviews, read it (or, at least, as much as I can tolerate if it turns out to be &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;that&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; bad), then be the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/category/reviews/book-reviews/first-to-review/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;First to Review&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; it.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Since I&amp;#39;ll be giving these books star ratings on Amazon and goodreads, I&amp;#39;ll give them here as well using the following scale:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;1 - Nearly incomprehensible&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;2 - Can be read, but nothing to recommend it. Typos. Weak voice. Incoherent plot. When people think of fan fiction, most of it&amp;#39;s about 2 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;3 - Technically competent. Readable. Unspectacular. The &amp;quot;popcorn movie&amp;quot; type of books tend to get 3 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 - Solidly good. New and interesting plot and characters and a strong voice. For me, the average Brandon Sanderson novel.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;5 - Mind blowing. I-read-it-in-one-sitting. Zero-to-no flaws.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;What I hope to find are solidly-written books by authors without any marketing skills. What I fear to find are endless waves of incomprehensible trash. Let&amp;#39;s find out!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I&amp;#39;m starting with &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2015/reviews/book-reviews/first-to-review/review-prince-of-leaf-and-stone-by-m-q-allen/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Prince of Leaf and Stone&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; by M. Q. Allen&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: Prince of Leaf and Stone by M. Q. Allen</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/review-prince-of-leaf-and-stone-by-m-q-allen.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/review-prince-of-leaf-and-stone-by-m-q-allen.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagespls-mqa-188x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Prince of Leaf and Stone by M. Q. Allen&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00U0IR0F0/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00U0IR0F0&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=4W2UIMJHQILNJFPQ&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;This post is part of a series called &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2015/reviews/book-reviews/first-to-review/new-series-first-to-review/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;First to Review&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, where I review Amazon Kindle books that haven&amp;#39;t been reviewed by anyone else. The idea is, any review is better than no reviews.&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Amount read: 100%&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When I knew what rating I&amp;#39;d give it: 85%&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I really liked the ending of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Prince of Leaf and Stone&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Unfortunately, the rest of the novel gets in the way.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There are many times during this book I almost put it down. 12%, 34%, 55%, 67% (gotta love the Kindle&amp;#39;s method of progress). The voice is okay and there are relatively few typos, but it reads like D&amp;amp;amp;D fan fiction, even focusing on human and totally-not-elf relationships (thin &amp;quot;Ever-folk&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;leaf-shaped&amp;quot; ears). Other than the main character, Aedric, the characters are inconsistent. Most, even (especially) the long-lived Ever-folk who we&amp;#39;re told take years to make decisions, are rash and impulsive. Apparently the love interest, Ophia, is more rash and passionate than other Ever-folk, but in actions other Ever-folk, such as Kiadrin and the King, are at least as impulsive. We&amp;#39;re told Ever-folk who lose their spouse usually mourn for decades or even centuries, but apparently &amp;quot;mourn&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;immediately fall in love again&amp;quot; are synonyms.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The plot seems rambling and disjointed, until you get to the end where everything ties together. This can be pulled off (Neal Stephenson being the master), but here I felt more lost than anything else. It&amp;#39;s difficult to connect with the book, since it&amp;#39;s difficult to see what it&amp;#39;s &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;about&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; until you reach the end. Constantly, we&amp;#39;re told vague plot details from later in the book (&amp;quot;I never saw him again.&amp;quot; &amp;quot;But I could never fulfill my promise.&amp;quot;) that only serve to kill the tension.*&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Oh, but that ending. The characterization of Aedric is quite good (in hindsight), and his arc is interesting and novel, even if it wavers with the plot at times, and the pay-off is worth it. For 12% - 80% through the book, I was certain I&amp;#39;d give it 2 stars, but the climax elevated the whole novel.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Stars: 2.5 peridots (round up to 3) out of 5 on the following scale:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;1 - Nearly incomprehensible&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;2 - Can be read, but nothing to recommend it. Typos. Weak voice. Incoherent plot and characters. When people think of fan fiction, most of it&amp;#39;s about 2 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;3 - Technically competent. Readable. Unspectacular. The &amp;quot;popcorn movie&amp;quot; type of books tend to get 3 stars.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;4 - Solidly good. New and interesting plot and characters and a strong voice. For me, the average Brandon Sanderson novel.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;5 - Mind blowing. I-read-it-in-one-sitting. Zero-to-no flaws.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;* Let&amp;#39;s talk about foreshadowing.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I read a book in school years (and years) ago. The title and author escape my memory. But, I remember the foreshadowing. In this book, a teenager in a &amp;quot;gang&amp;quot; (think Westside Story more than Bloods and Crips) stabs another teenager during some friendly neighborhood gang warfare. The other kid dies. Now, despite fighting with knives, bats, and chains, no one on either side expected anyone to &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;actually die&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; during this fight, but there you go. Our protagonist, shaking uncontrollably, lights up a cigarette to calm his nerves, and stares into the coal at the end, wondering what it would be like inside a fire. Then he goes on the run. In the climax of the book, he runs into a burning building to save a family, and no longer has to wonder what it&amp;#39;s like inside a fire. This is foreshadowing.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;quot;I never saw him again.&amp;quot; &amp;quot;But I could never fulfill my promise.&amp;quot; This is not foreshadowing. Done once or twice, it can serve to tie off loose ends, but when it happens nearly every chapter it&amp;#39;s jolting and ruins the engagement.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The fax machine is how old?</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/the-fax-machine-is-how-old.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/the-fax-machine-is-how-old.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesBain_improved_facsimile_1850.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Alexander Bain&amp;#39;s fax machine, 1843&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Alexander Bain&amp;#39;s fax machine, 1843{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In 1843, Alexander Bain applied for the first patent on a &amp;quot;chemical telegram&amp;quot; which could record &amp;quot;lines and ticks&amp;quot; and send them over the telegraph. By 1846, he could sketch and send images. Read the complete history of the telegraph at &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.todayifoundout.com/index.php/2014/11/shockingly-old-history-fax-machine/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Today I Found Out&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: The Farthest Shore by Ursula K. Le Guin</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/farthest-shore-ursula-le-guin.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/farthest-shore-ursula-le-guin.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesfarthest-178x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Farthest Shore by Ursula K. Le Guin&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/144245993X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=144245993X&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=RKZUHWFNL3JLCC2G&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I have a confession to make: I&amp;#39;ve never been able to get into Le Guin&amp;#39;s books. I&amp;#39;ve read &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Left Hand of Darkness&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Earthsea&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; trilogy, and there&amp;#39;s something to the voice that I find dry and intolerable, like an anthropologist clinically describing observed events. Under this voice, even the most exciting scene is relayed in the monotonous drone of a professor lecturing ungrateful freshman. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Farthest Shore&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; has the additional problem of the apparent main character, Arren, having little-to-no agency for 95% of the book, the plot being driven by Ged and the Other.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Which is a shame, because, otherwise, these books are amazing.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Outside of Doctor Who, it&amp;#39;s difficult to find stories where violence does not solve all of your problems. I just reviewed &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Wolves of the Calla&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, solution: gunslinger violence. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, solution: violence against androids, then feel bad about it. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Slow Regard of Silent Things&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, solution: make soap (this might be one of the reasons why I liked this book as well). &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, solution: violence of every genre. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Star Wars&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, solution: lightsaber violence*.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;You get the picture.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Farthest Shore&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, violence is never the ultimate the solution. Sacrifice, life, balance, mercy, wisdom, these are the answers. Some quick violence in the service of protection may be necessary, but never as punishment or revenge, and always as a small piece of a greater solution. When I think of books I want my daughter to read as she grows up, Le Guin&amp;#39;s sit far ahead of King&amp;#39;s, or even Sanderson&amp;#39;s (who&amp;#39;s been my favorite author for a long while now). I just wish I could get into them myself.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;*One might argue that, ultimately, in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Return of the Jedi&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; the solution was mercy, given that Luke won by showing mercy to Vader, but one would be forgetting that this mercy was not the final solution; Vader throwing the Emperor down a conveniently placed reactor shaft holds that honor. And Lando blowing up the Death Star. And Han blowing up the shield generator. And Admiral Akbar fighting off the Imperial navy. And, ultimately, you have to consider the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.theforce.net/swtc/holocaust.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Endor holocaust&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. My point is, the solution was violence on a massive scale, likely killing &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;billions&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; living on the Death Star alone.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: Wolves of the Calla by Stephen King</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/03/wolves-calla-stephen-king.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 8 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/wolves-calla-stephen-king.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imageswotc-sk-165x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Wolves of the Calla by Stephen King&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/141651693X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=141651693X&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=PGKY4XG3DK6RFWNB&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I picked up &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Gunslinger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; in a bookstore on a hunch and a sense of obligation. I can&amp;#39;t put my finger on why, but I&amp;#39;d never read a Stephen King book before, though they&amp;#39;re certainly in my wheelhouse of interests and I&amp;#39;ve always had great respect for the man as a writer. When I opened &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Gunslinger&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, I&amp;#39;ll never forget the first line or my reaction to it. I read that line, what I still believe to be the greatest first line of any novel, in the graveled voice of Castiel from the TV show &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Supernatural&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The man in black fled across the desert, and the gunslinger followed.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I read the entire book in Castiel&amp;#39;s voice, and that book&amp;#39;s been my gateway into not just the Dark Tower series, but all of King&amp;#39;s novels. But with &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Drawing of the Three&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, we got a book that was, honestly, mostly set dressing and character movements; the ka-tet must be drawn, and this was a serviceable book to do so. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Waste Lands&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; brought us to the city of Lud and Blaine the mono, a book I thought as barren as its title. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Wizard and Glass&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; brought us a story of Roland&amp;#39;s old ka-tet, and a fine one at that, but bracketed with incomprehensible &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Wizard of Oz&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; nonsense, and very little time was spent with the ka-tet of which we Constant Readers care. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Wind Through the Keyhole&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; was a quick fun book, wheels within wheels, stories within stories, but only tangentially related to the matter at hand. As Eddie would say, the series had gone nineteen, and only halfway through.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I find it odd: in Hollywood the middle movies of a series are often the best, but in novels the middle books are often the worst. Movies seem to find themselves, but then run out of ideas before they end the series. Novels, on the other hand, start with great ideas, end with great ideas, but have so much trouble getting from the opening to the end.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;With &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Wolves of the Calla&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, I feel the series has finally gotten back on track, but how I find it difficult to define. Is it less ridiculous, with fewer &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Wizard of Oz&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;-ish pop culture plot elements? It is not. But it feels more... &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;lived in&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. The Calla feels real, in ways that Lud did not, with a fine merging of western aesthetic and decaying technology. The characters, both the ka-tet and the folken of the Calla, seem fuller and more &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;themselves&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and less &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;plot elements&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, hear me, I beg. Most importantly, we spend ample time with the ka-tet, and for the first time since they were drawn, I feel I&amp;#39;ve gotten to know them better.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Spoilers:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I do worry for &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Song of Susannah&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. The entire sideplot with Mia and her &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;chap&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; bothered me through and through. Not that it was shoehorned in, clearly this was always the direction the story was going to go, but I&amp;#39;ve never been a big fan of the &amp;quot;demon pregnancy&amp;quot; trope, and we seem to be playing that tune to the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;hilt&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep? by Philip K. Dick</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/02/review-do-androids-dream-of-electric-sheep-by-philip-k-dick.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/02/review-do-androids-dream-of-electric-sheep-by-philip-k-dick.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesandroids-dream-201x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep? by Philip K. Dick&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0345404475/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0345404475&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=BF7FA4Z73Z34C5MJ&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Coming to &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; from &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Blade Runner&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is an interesting experience, given the drastic changes in tone (the glitzy corporate overpopulation of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Blade Runner&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; vs. the post-apocalyptic depression of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Do Androids Dream?&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;). Shaking the dust of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Blade Runner&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; from your sandals is necessary before continuing.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The primary tension in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Electric Sheep&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; comes down to empathy vs. cold intellect (human vs. android), and whether an android could develop empathy, which is never properly resolved. In one moment, an android is clipping the legs off a spider just to see if it can walk with four, but in the next is distraught over losing a friend.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Real-world engineer hat: it wouldn&amp;#39;t be that difficult to make androids &amp;quot;feel&amp;quot; empathy, any more so than it would be to make them &amp;quot;feel&amp;quot; anything else, including self-preservation. This is, of course, assuming you could get them to read the emotions (or simulate reading the emotions based on scripts of circumstances), which is also not a difficult feat, considering what they&amp;#39;ve already done. All you have to do is (to paraphrase &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;I, Robot&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;) induce neural feedback upon encountering the suffering of others. But, then again, the core of this novel is not the care, feeding, and bounty hunting of androids, but something more resembling the hypocrisy of man, religion, and the tension of empathy vs. intelligence within ourselves.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Electric Sheep&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is a deep book wearing the mask of a shallow book, but, in the end, it is only half a mask (the Mercerism plum line cannot be hidden). For those expected a by-the-numbers noire, it&amp;#39;s there in spades (Sam Spades, one might say), but everything about the animals and Mercerism might feel strange and out of place. For those expected a scifi, Kafkaesque story involving robots, we&amp;#39;ve got your alienated protagonist undergoing a mystical transformation right here.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Further thoughts:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Sex with robots is more common than most people think.&amp;quot;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;It&amp;#39;s weird reading future scifi stories written before cell phones and the internet.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Owning an electric toad would be pretty awesome. In fact, I think I&amp;#39;d prefer it to a real toad.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Review: The Slow Regard of Silent Things by Patrick Rothfuss</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/02/review-the-slow-regard-of-silent-things-by-patrick-rothfuss.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/02/review-the-slow-regard-of-silent-things-by-patrick-rothfuss.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagespr-srst-212x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;The Slow Regard of Silent Things by Patrick Rothfuss&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0756410436/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0756410436&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkId=AN3HSAOLN5AJPZKF&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Buy on Amazon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I&amp;#39;ve thought a lot about the title of this book, even before I read it. Reportedly, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blog.patrickrothfuss.com/2014/10/the-slow-regard-of-silent-things/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;the translators couldn&amp;#39;t figure out what it meant&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, so the international versions use the title The Music of Silence. This is most unfortunate, because I believe the title holds the key to knowing, before you&amp;#39;ve even read the book, whether you will like it.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Can you imagine the slow regard of silent things? Beneath the Earth, in the cast-off tunnels of the Underthing, can you imagine objects, tunnels, rooms contain a bit of personality, of humanity, of wakefulness and will, under the appropriate circumstances, silently regard any trespassers? Are you ready for a beautiful meditation on the nature of nature and the brokenness of broken people? Then this book is for you.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Do you look at the title &amp;quot;The Slow Regard of Silent Things&amp;quot; and say, &amp;quot;What the actual what?&amp;quot; Then this book may not be for you.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;3 out of candle; would read to my daughter again.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Haha, the last post was titled &quot;Moving Forward&quot; (a year and a half ago); also, Writing Excuses</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2015/01/also-writing-excuses.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/01/also-writing-excuses.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I&amp;#39;ve been away &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;so long&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; my domain name lapsed. Seriously, who does that?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Anyway, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.writingexcuses.com/2015/01/04/writing-excuses-10-1-seriously-where-do-you-get-your-ideas/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;season 10 of Writing Excuses&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; is being structured as a master class in writing, so I&amp;#39;m going to follow along and post my homework here.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Homework 1&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Write down five different story ideas in 150 words or less. Generate these ideas from these five sources:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;From an interview or conversation you&amp;#39;ve had
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Antisocial loner creates robot army using the trapped souls of the recently deceased&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;From research you&amp;#39;ve done (reading science news, military history, etc)
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Sunset Invasion (Native Americans with guns invade medieval Europe)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;From observation (go for a walk!)
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Generational ship breaks apart; each half falling onto one of a set of binary planets.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;From a piece of media (watch a movie)
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Time traveling undercover historian&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;From a piece of music (with or without lyrics)
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;LKIhjsdsioaosdi asdfaklsdk aksdk fkksakd (this one&amp;#39;s written in code, since I am paranoid, it is very specific, and I&amp;#39;m currently writing it)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Homework 2&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Using last week&amp;#39;s five story ideas (or five new ones):&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Take two of them and combine them into one story.
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Time traveling, undercover historian encounters antisocial loner creating a robot army from the trapped souls of the recently deceased&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Take one and change the genre underneath it.
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;lkasdklf klsdfklklsdJLDSFKJ dklsfkl sdklfalksd;fasdf (new code for this one)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Take one and change the ages and genders of everybody you had in mind for it
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Sunset Invasion, but the Native Americans have a matriarchal society&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Take the last one and have a character make the opposite choice.
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Generational ship breaks apart, but the command crew sacrifices the rest of the ship to save themselves (this is a much less interesting story)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Moving forward and Cloud Atlas</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2013/08/cloud-atlas.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2013/08/cloud-atlas.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;To anyone paying attention, it must be apparent that I am not a good blogger. I do not blog regularly. I do not stay with one topic for longer than a few weeks, and even those few weeks become less ambitious as time passes (every day! Every week day! Three times a week! Three times a week... but two is a fluff piece. Once a week. It&amp;#39;s been over a year since I&amp;#39;ve posted...)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There&amp;#39;s one person, other than myself, who may know where the name &amp;quot;Forest Azuaron&amp;quot; came from. In 2006 (or so), I wrote a 50,000 word novel for NaNoWriMo titled &amp;quot;Forest Azuaron&amp;quot;. It was &amp;quot;horror&amp;quot; in the kind of &amp;quot;it has blood and guts so must be scary&amp;quot; way that teenagers (as I was at the time) think must be scary, but as actual horror fails completely. That being said, there are a number of ideas within it that I still think are rather good, including the forest itself. The forest was a kind of extra-dimensional, malevolent entity that could freely manipulate the speed of time passing within any part of itself, rearrange itself at will, and move about the normal plane of existence freely.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Which, let&amp;#39;s face it, is a decent enough metaphor for my mind, or, really, the mind of anyone insane enough to call themselves a writer.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;With those cards on the table, this site is now focused on whatever bonkers thing I happen to want to write about at any given time, which could be as frequently as once an hour, or as infrequently as once a century.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And tonight, I watched &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2013/08/cloud-atlas.jpg&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesCloud-Atlas-1024x768.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Cloud Atlas&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Let me say how I typically watch a movie. I&amp;#39;ll pop it into my laptop (on the right side of my desk), turn it on... then turn on a videogame on my PC (center of the desk). Depending on how much attention I&amp;#39;m going to pay to the movie, my choice of videogame will vary. An intelligent movie with lots of dialog would warrant a game of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Faster than Light&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (which is fairly slow-paced except when it&amp;#39;s not, but you can pause at any time), or maybe I&amp;#39;ll grind dailies or achievements in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Star Wars: The Old Republic&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Something more mindless, I may quest in &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Old Republic&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (nothing with a group) or a strategy game like Europa Universalis. If I want to show a particular disdain for the brainlessness of a movie, I may play a story-heavy RPG (such as &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Dragon Age&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; or &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Game of Thrones: The Game&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; [of thrones]).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;While watching &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, I played &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Game of Thrones: Ascent&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. Anyone could be forgiven for not knowing about such a game, so let me explain it a little. It&amp;#39;s one of those Facebook/Flash type games where you build up a city and send heroes on quests, but everything takes time. It takes three hours to build a stable. Four to send a hero on this or that quest. Twenty minutes to make this or that item. &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;And&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;, if you don&amp;#39;t want to wait, you could always pay a little real money to speed things along, couldn&amp;#39;t you? (Somewhere an accountant is rubbing their hands together.)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But, as an aspiring homeowner, I do not spend money on frivolities like &amp;quot;not waiting two hours for a fake smithy to make a sword&amp;quot;, so I wait. This is the game I &amp;quot;played&amp;quot; while watching &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;; one that requires my attention, at maximum, once every fifteen minutes. And frequently I found myself behind on my game.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is a movie seemingly built for someone like me. This isn&amp;#39;t to say I have ADD (I don&amp;#39;t), and &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; is a movie for such people. Rather, what &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; does is fully engage. While many people approach movies in an effort to turn off their brains, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Cloud Atlas&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; demands full cognitive function and attention. Contrast with most other movies that demand maybe one eye, a quarter of the visual cortex, and half the limbic system but little else.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I feel like a pretentious snit just typing that, so let me list my favorite movies this year to make myself feel better: &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Pacific Rim&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Avengers&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;White House Down&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (okay, sometimes turning off the brain is nice), &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Iron Man 3&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, and &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Thor: The Dark World&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; (no, I don&amp;#39;t care that it isn&amp;#39;t out yet).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A movie doesn&amp;#39;t have to be pretentious to be thought-provoking, just conscious. For instance, I&amp;#39;ve seen each of the four Bourne movies multiple times each and I still can&amp;#39;t remember anything about them, whereas &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;The Avengers&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; hides a nearly perfect script underneath a flashy summer blockbuster.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Why isn&#39;t the night sky bright?</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/10/why-isnt-the-night-sky-bright.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 1 Oct 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/10/why-isnt-the-night-sky-bright.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gxJ4M7tyLRE&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gxJ4M7tyLRE&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The answer seems obvious (the Sun isn&amp;#39;t out), but, assuming an infinite universe (which current data supports), shouldn&amp;#39;t the night sky be completely covered by stars and starlight?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Watch the video to find out why it isn&amp;#39;t.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;(video by &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/user/minutephysics&amp;quot;&amp;gt;minutephysics&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; via &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/badastronomy/2012/10/01/why-is-the-sky-dark-at-night/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Bad Astronomy&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Tattoine has been found</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/08/tattoine-has-been-found.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/08/tattoine-has-been-found.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesbinary-exoplanet.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Kepler-47c&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Artist rendering of Tatooine... er, Kepler-47c... from NASA.{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The orbiting telescope Kepler has just discovered the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;second&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; exoplanet in binary star system Kepler-47, and &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/badastronomy/2012/08/29/kepler-finds-a-planet-in-a-binary-stars-habitable-zone/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;this one is in the habitable zone&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Earth in 100,000,000 years</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/08/the-earth-in-100000000-years.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 6 Aug 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/08/the-earth-in-100000000-years.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesamasia.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Amasia&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Image from Ross Mitchell, Nature{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Most high school students learn that the Earth used to have only a single continent: Pangaea. In 100 million years, the continents are &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://discovermagazine.com/2012/jul-aug/06-earth-look-like-this-in-100-000-000-ad&amp;quot;&amp;gt;drifting toward&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v482/n7384/full/nature10800.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;the formation of a new supercontinent&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/80beats/2012/02/09/americas-europe-asia-amasia-the-next-supercontinent-to-form-in-arctic/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Amasia&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Billionaire rumored to be cloning a dinosaur</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/08/billionaire-rumored-to-be-cloning-a-dinosaur.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 3 Aug 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/08/billionaire-rumored-to-be-cloning-a-dinosaur.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagescrichton_jurassic-park.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Jurassic Park by Michael Crichton&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Poor people are crazy, Jack. I&amp;#39;m eccentric!&amp;quot;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Clive Palmer, Australian billionaire, is rumored to be in talks with the scientists who cloned Dolly the sheep. &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://suvudu.com/2012/08/rich-guy-who-apparently-never-saw-jurassic-park-wants-to-clone-dinosaur.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;He wants to clone a dinosaur&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;That is all.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Building an Artificial Jellyfish</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/07/building-an-artificial-jellyfish.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/07/building-an-artificial-jellyfish.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2012/07/medusoid.jpg&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesmedusoid.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;medusoid&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; Made from rat heart cells and silicone. (Image courtesy of Harvard and Caltech){caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Recently, [scientists have constructed a &amp;quot;medusoid&amp;quot;][scientists have constructed a _medusoid] out of rat heart cells (article behind paywall).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But what would it take to build an actual jellyfish? Ferris Jabr at Scientific American [explores the options][].&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;[scientists have constructed a _medusoid]: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.nature.com/nbt/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nbt.2269.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.nature.com/nbt/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nbt.2269.html&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;[explores the options]: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/brainwaves/2012/07/25/what-would-it-take-to-really-build-an-artificial-jellyfish/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/brainwaves/2012/07/25/what-would-it-take-to-really-build-an-artificial-jellyfish/&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>What happens if you throw a baseball at nearly the speed of light?</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/07/what-happens-if-you-throw-a-baseball-at-nearly-the-speed-of-light.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/07/what-happens-if-you-throw-a-baseball-at-nearly-the-speed-of-light.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesfusion-baseball.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Fusion Baseball&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Head on over to &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://what-if.xkcd.com/1/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;xkcd&amp;#39;s new What if?&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; to find out!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Madswitching DNA: The bacterial Hulk</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/07/madswitching-dna-the-bacterial-hulk.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 5 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/07/madswitching-dna-the-bacterial-hulk.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesworm-bacteria-partnership.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Worm bacteria partnership&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Photo by Peggy Greb (Creative Commons).{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There is a parasitic worm that invades insects&amp;#39; bodies, then vomits up a terrifying bacteria that, upon leaving the worm, transforms from a mostly-benign Bruce Banner to a terrifying Incredible Hulk. Once transformed, the bacteria liquifies the insect and fights off any rival bacteria, while it&amp;#39;s partner-in-crime--the worm--sucks up the insect&amp;#39;s juices.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;What causes the change? A single piece of DNA called a &amp;quot;madswitch&amp;quot; (technical term).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Read more about this frightening partnership at Discover Magazine: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2010/12/17/parasitic-worms-paint-warning-colours-on-their-hosts-using-glowing-bacteria/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;the worms&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2012/07/05/worm-kills-insects-by-vomiting-hulk-like-bacteria/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;the bacteria&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Higgs boson was discovered! Maybe! Should we care? Yes! No!</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/07/the-higgs-boson-was-discovered-maybe-should-we-care-yes-no.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 4 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/07/the-higgs-boson-was-discovered-maybe-should-we-care-yes-no.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imageslhccms_higgsdiscovery.gif&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Potential Higgs Data&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;For days the science world (or, more specifically, the physics world) has been aflutter. It was announced that, early this morning, CERN would announce the findings of the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) regarding the Higgs boson. And they did, and the news is about as good as anyone could expect it to be.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;That bump at about 125 GeV? That indicates the presence of a new particle, and this particle, so far, fits the properties of the hypothesized Higgs boson.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;What is the Higgs boson?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Complicated. Basically, it&amp;#39;s said to be the reason that other particles appear to have mass. &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/cosmicvariance/2007/11/06/higgs-101/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;John Conway wrote a detailed &amp;quot;Higgs 101&amp;quot; in 2007&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; that, despite being called &amp;quot;101&amp;quot; is fairly hard to follow for anyone without advanced physics training.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Scientific American&amp;#39;s George Musser explains the Higgs boson in a simpler way, but doesn&amp;#39;t go into much detail (video below).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://c.brightcove.com/services/viewer/federated_f8/1399191810&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://c.brightcove.com/services/viewer/federated_f8/1399191810&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;That the Higgs seems to exist partially validates the Standard Model, a mathematical model that explains subatomic particle behavior, but only &amp;quot;works&amp;quot; when they hypothesized a previously unknown particle to exist. That particle is the Higgs boson, and, had it not existed, the Standard Model would have fallen apart.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;What would it mean if this new particle the LHC discovered was a Higgs boson, and, beyond that, a Higgs boson that behaved as predicted by the Standard Model? It would be one of the most significant discoveries in our lifetime. Studying the Higgs boson could bring us one step closer to discovering how--and why--gravity works, why some particles have mass, and others do not (photons, how do they work?), what the universe was like immediately following the Big Bang, and how we can travel through space more efficiently.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;On the other hand...&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The discovery of the Higgs boson could validate the Standard Model, but do little else. And the Standard Model is far from complete, given that it doesn&amp;#39;t take silly things like gravity into account.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There has been a divide in physics for a long time: general relativity, which explains how objects behave on a macro, micro, and atomic level, and quantum mechanics, which explains how particles behave on a quantum level. Since Einstein, many theoretical physicists have been looking for the Theory of Everything that explains, well, everything, and ties the two seemingly disparate systems together, but without success.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And the Higgs boson, while a triumph for the Standard Model and quantum mechanics, has very little chance of providing answers for the Theory of Everything.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In fact, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/2012/07/04/if-you-want-more-higgs-hype-dont-read-this-column/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;John Horgan asserts that&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, in addition to the Higgs boson being a relatively meaningless discovery compared to the cost associated with finding it, most physicists will abandon pursuit of the Theory of Everything because it&amp;#39;s simply not needed. The Standard Model, while not perfect, predicts quantum behavior well enough to be useful, and general relativity does the same for larger scales. The pursuit of a Theory of Everything merely diverts efforts toward more meaningful discovers.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Horgan has predicted that, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://longbets.org/12/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;by 2020, no one will have won a Nobel prize for any kind of unified theory&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and he put up $1,000 against Michio Kaku in a bet that&amp;#39;s over halfway done.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;What if this isn&amp;#39;t even a Higgs boson?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A lot of people are certainly getting ahead of themselves with this discovery. What the LHC has found is a new particle with a mass of 125-126 GeV. While they were looking for the Higgs boson, and that is where the Higgs boson would be if it existed, there&amp;#39;s not much to say that this actually is a Higgs boson other than that&amp;#39;s what they predict.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;So, if it&amp;#39;s not a Higgs boson, what is it?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Nobody knows. And wouldn&amp;#39;t &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;that&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; be exciting?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>How to rocket pack</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/how-to-rocket-pack.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/how-to-rocket-pack.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesjetpack.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;jetpack&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Photo by Fir0002/Flagstaffotos (Creative Commons){caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Who wouldn&amp;#39;t want a backpack that let them fly? Since the 1920s, science fiction enthusiasts have imagined just that. During World War II, the technology to finally make it happen became a reality.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Within 10 years everyone got personal rocket packs. Why don&amp;#39;t we all have rocket packs?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;How rocket packs work&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A rocket pack works similarly to a rocket engine: combusting/expanding fuel is forced out a nozzle in one direction. Following Newton&amp;#39;s Third Law of Motion, the rocket pack (and whoever it&amp;#39;s attached to) move in the opposite direction. Simple, yeah?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The problem with rocket packs&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;As shown (briefly) in the first Iron Man movie, controlling a personal rocket is very difficult. The thrust nozzles must be pointed in exactly the correct direction or the pilot will shoot off in a random direction, and could even be dragged across the ground. During most rocket pack flights, the pilots are attached to a tether for safety.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Further, there&amp;#39;s the issue of combusting (exploding!) rocket fuel aimed near the pilot&amp;#39;s legs.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Then, of course, humans are simply not aerodynamic creatures.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Finally, while the first three problems can be solved with clever engineering, there remains the fuel problem. Rocket packs, by necessity, have limited fuel because it all has to fit on a human&amp;#39;s back. Typically, they have less than 10 gallons. That much fuel, by itself, is only good for 30 seconds of flight (and remember, you have to come back down safely).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;While this doesn&amp;#39;t influence the effectiveness of rocket packs, they are rather loud. Loud like a, I don&amp;#39;t know, rocket strapped to your back.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The future of rocket packs&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Fuel will always be the problem with rocket packs. They need a fuel that&amp;#39;s forceful enough to lift a person, long-lasting enough to get the pilot somewhere, and stable enough to not blow off the pilot&amp;#39;s legs.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Currently, the best rocket fuel is hydrogen peroxide, which when combined with liquid nitrogen and a silver catalyst, shoots super heated steam from the nozzles and gives thrust. That may sound less exciting than, say, NASA&amp;#39;s refined petroleum which, when mixed with liquid oxygen and ignited explodes and lifts a space ship into the sky, but has the benefit of not blowing off the pilot&amp;#39;s legs.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Honestly, I don&amp;#39;t think rocket packs will become a common mode of personal or military transportation, particularly since they&amp;#39;re inherently dangerous, ridiculously loud, and difficult to control. Further, there are better options available, such as the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://science.howstuffworks.com/transport/flight/modern/pav.htm&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Personal Air Vehicle&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultralight_aviation#Types_of_aircraft&amp;quot;&amp;gt;ultralight planes&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.innovator.mosquito.net.nz/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;ultralight helicopters&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;That being said, if some kind of anti-gravity or safe repulsorlift technology gets invented, we may be looking at a rocket pack-like device without the fuel limitations of an actual rocket pack.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Happy Tau Day!</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/happy-tau-day.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/happy-tau-day.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FtxmFlMLYRI&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FtxmFlMLYRI&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Who wants to eat TWO PIES (2π)?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Spirals, Fibonacci, and being a plant</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/spirals-fibonacci-and-being-a-plant.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/spirals-fibonacci-and-being-a-plant.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=14-NdQwKz9w&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=14-NdQwKz9w&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Doodling in Math: Spirals, Fibonacci, and Being a Plant&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Showing &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=14-NdQwKz9w&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Part 3&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://youtu.be/ahXIMUkSXX0&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Part 1&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://youtu.be/lOIP_Z_-0Hs&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Part 2&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>What is intelligence? IQ</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/what-is-intelligence-iq.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/what-is-intelligence-iq.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesiq.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;IQ&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; From Wikimedia Commons; GNU Free Document License{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The catchall term for intelligence in modern settings is IQ (that is, Intelligence Quotient). Pop culture has established pretty firmly that a &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; person has an IQ of 100, a &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; person has an IQ near the 130s, and a supergenius has ridiculous IQ numbers anywhere from 170 to 300.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But what is an IQ test? How does it relate to how intelligent a person is?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The Intelligence Quotient&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In the early 1900s, many people became interested in making better people through social and genetic engineering (the eugenics movement). They thought that by identifying school children who would grow up to be mentally retarded, they could sterilize those children and, through a forced Darwinian selection, breed more intelligent people.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;During World War I, these tests were used to rapidly assign recruits to various training programs. Score high? Officer training. Score above average? Piloting, sniping, or driving. Score low? Infantry. This expanded use of the intelligence tests drove funding and efforts toward a universal theory of general intelligence and beyond the eugenics movement.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Ultimately, while evidence for a theory of general intelligence has been found (*g*), it remains disputed. Further, researchers can&amp;#39;t agree on a single &amp;quot;perfect&amp;quot; test, so an &amp;quot;IQ score&amp;quot; may be from &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intelligence_quotient#Modern_tests&amp;quot;&amp;gt;any of a number of tests&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. These tests tend to measure reasoning, spatial ability, pattern recognition, and verbal comprehension.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Fortunately, the tests seem to predict the same thing, and they&amp;#39;re all mapped onto the same &amp;quot;IQ score&amp;quot; system and are often used in conjunction with each other.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The IQ score&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When someone says they have an IQ of 170 (or 100, or 70, or 121), what does that mean? Unfortunately, it&amp;#39;s pretty deep into statistics, but I&amp;#39;ll try and gloss over the math as much as possible.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When one of the IQ tests is taken, a raw score is calculated. Depending on the test, this raw score can range from 5 to 2,000; this score isn&amp;#39;t actually that important.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The psychologists take that score and compare it to a whole bunch of scores they have from the same group of people (for instance, American adults). Then, depending on how that raw score compares to the other raw scores, an IQ score is assigned.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;More specifically, IQ scores &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;always&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; have an average of 100 and a standard deviation of 15 (for those who know what that means).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Essentially, the average IQ is always 100. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Always.&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; The average IQ has not risen, nor has it dropped, in the past &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;{number}&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; years. The average IQ is 100 &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;by definition&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; and it always will be.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;(Whether the raw scores have risen or dropped, or are going to rise or drop, is another issue; &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flynn_effect&amp;quot;&amp;gt;they have risen in recent decades&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, cause currently disputed.)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The standard deviation is a bit more complicated. What it means is that 95% of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;everyone&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; in the group will have a score between 70 and 130. It also means that a large change in the raw scores near the average (700 to 800) can result in a small change in IQ score (100 to 103), while a small change in the raw scores away from the average (1000 to 1010) can have a dramatic change in the IQ score (150 to 170).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Further, any IQ measured above 145 (3 standard deviations) is, essentially, too smart for the test, and no more specific conclusions can be drawn about them.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;So, when there&amp;#39;s intellectual &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;*ahem*&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; measuring going on, and one character compares their 153 IQ to another&amp;#39;s 150 IQ, several thoughts should spring to mind:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Did they both take the same kind of test?&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;What were their raw scores (are they comparing the difference between a single question)?&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Have they taken multiple tests, or was one (or both) lucky on one test?&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Even if everything&amp;#39;s as accurate as it can be, the difference between 150 and 153 is negligeable and functionally unmeasurable.&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And anyone claiming to have an IQ over 200 is lying, or was lied to. Most tests &amp;quot;top out&amp;quot; around 160, meaning that the test taker has answered every question correctly, and can&amp;#39;t possibly get a better score.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h4&amp;gt;What does IQ measure? What does it predict?&amp;lt;/h4&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;IQ has been proposed as a general intelligence measure, which is as specific as it sounds: how smart a person is. Since the test creators were mostly male, and American or English, &amp;quot;smart&amp;quot; is measured as a Western male English-speaker would define it, and the IQ test has been frequently criticized as such. In particular, the IQ test fails to account for emotional intelligence (empathy), creativity, cultural and lingual differences, and social ability.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Regardless of its failings, IQ can predict things like college grades, occupation, and income level with a fair amount of accuracy (*r* = .7 for college grades, if you care).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h4&amp;gt;What can I do with IQ?&amp;lt;/h4&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Don&amp;#39;t misuse it. While there are certainly societies (such as Mensa) that take great stock in such scores, they tend to, ironically, misuse them. Generally speaking, though, a certain amount of whatever IQ measures is required for success, but is not sufficient. To succeed, people need creativity, adaptability, social skills, and dozens of other traits.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Weird Science: Spiders that drink mammal (human!) blood</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/weird-science-spiders-that-drink-mammal-human-blood.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/weird-science-spiders-that-drink-mammal-human-blood.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesvampire-spider.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;vampire spider&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Image by Robert Jackson{caption}&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;(Every so often we talk about something really weird in science. See the complete series at &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/category/weird-science/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Weird Science&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.)&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There are spiders that &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2005/10/1011_051011_spider_vampire.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;drink mammal blood&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2012/06/07/to-study-vampire-spiders-build-frankenstein-mosquitoes/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;sucking it out of mosquitoes&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Hit in the head</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/hit-in-the-head.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/hit-in-the-head.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesbrain.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;brain&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;This is your brain&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The villain needs to capture the hero, so he sends in his strongarm henchman to deliver a sharp blow to the back of the hero&amp;#39;s head and knock the hero out for a couple of hours.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;If this were real life, the hero would lapse into a coma and die.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Head injuries are dangerous&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The &amp;quot;knock someone out for a few hours&amp;quot; trope is somewhat surprising due to the number of people who watch boxing. Those guys pound on each other for twelve rounds, taking blow after blow to the face. Oh, they have padded gloves? The gloves exist to protect the boxer&amp;#39;s primary asset, through which he makes all his money: his hands. They can&amp;#39;t box with broken hands, and in the days of widespread bare-knuckle boxing, the most successful boxers were the ones who could pull their punches so they didn&amp;#39;t break their own hands, but punch hard enough to damage their opponents.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Even then, James Kelly and Jonathan Smith were able to fight for 6 hours with no one getting knocked out (Smith conceded).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When someone is &amp;quot;knocked out&amp;quot; in boxing, they usually aren&amp;#39;t unconscious. They&amp;#39;re on the ground, and unable to stand and continue the fight, and they only have &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;ten seconds&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; to pull themselves together and get up.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But, as any longtime boxing, football, or rugby fan can tell you, getting head in the head a lot does severe cumulative damage over time. Muhammad Ali, known for being well-spoken early in his career, lost much of that as he neared retirement, and was diagnosed with Parkinson&amp;#39;s in 1984, almost certainly from getting lots of concussions. But he was never &amp;quot;knocked out&amp;quot; for several hours. Or even several minutes.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Symptoms that occur before unconsciousness from head injuries&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Disorientation&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Loss of coordination&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Slurred speech&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Extreme irritability&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Inability to focus&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Excessive fatigue&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Vomiting&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Seizures&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;These symptoms are &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;less serious&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; than unconsciousness. People who have sustained head injuries are encouraged to stay awake until they get to a doctor, because if they fall asleep they may not wake up. If someone has a head injury severe enough that they are unconscious, they should be taken to the hospital immediately--they probably have a skull fracture and/or are bleeding into their brain.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Also, the necessary recovery period requires &amp;quot;little to no exertion&amp;quot; not &amp;quot;immediately kickbox your way out of the villain&amp;#39;s lair.&amp;quot; Exertion (physical or mental) increases blood flow to the brain which worsens the injury.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The problem with giant exoskeletons</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/the-problem-with-giant-exoskeletons.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/the-problem-with-giant-exoskeletons.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Last week we looked into a &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2012/biology/macrobiology/physiology/plausible-giant-creatures/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;problem most fantasy worlds have&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, and this week we&amp;#39;re looking at a related, but more specific, problem endemic to science fiction. The Ender series. Starship Troopers. Them! (and dozens of other horror classics). This problem is a subset of the giant creatures problem: giant creatures with exoskeletons. In addition to the usual reasons giant creatures don&amp;#39;t work, giant creatures with exoskeletons are particularly hamstrung. But first, let&amp;#39;s take a look at the largest creatures with exoskeletons.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The largest exoskeletons&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesgoliath-beetle.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;goliath beetle&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;A true monsterThe heaviest known living insect is the goliath beetle. These monsters are truly magnificent, and should be the subject of horror movies for generations; one look at their dual horns and chitinous, grasping legs is enough to send even the most hardened horror watcher into fits of terror.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Length: A staggering four and a half &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;inches&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Weight: A colossal three and a half &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;ounces&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;True monsters indeed.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesdragonfly.gif&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Meganeura monyi&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Largest known insect (Wikimedia Commons; Gnu Free Document License)But wait! That&amp;#39;s only the largest living insect. Back in the Carboniferous period there were dragonfly-like insects you wouldn&amp;#39;t believe! I give to you: Meganeura monyi.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Wingspan: 2.1 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;feet&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Weight: 1 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;pound&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Comparable in size to: a crow&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Why are insects so small?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Largely, this has to do with their respiration: they don&amp;#39;t have lungs (or other centralized respiratory systems, like gills). They have millions of trachea that draw air into their bodies through their exoskeletons. This is very efficient, but only works to a maximum body width of about 3 inches. Meganeura monyi is believed to have grown to the size it did because the atmosphere had a greater oxygen content at the time, which increased their respiration efficiency enough to support a larger insect. If a meganeura monyi were to time travel to today, it would rapidly suffocate.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;So lungs solve exoskeletal size problems?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;To answer that, lets take a look at the largest crustaceans, which are, to my knowledge, the largest creatures with exoskeletons that can move under their own power (sorry giant clams).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagescoconut-crab.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Coconut crab&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;The coconut crab is the largest land-dwelling crustacean--indeed, the largest land-dwelling invertebrate. They breathe through branchiostegal lungs (halfway between gills and actual lungs) and will drown if submerged in water. It&amp;#39;s also a hermit crab, which means that not only does it have an exoskeleton, but it&amp;#39;ll steal your exoskeleton and wear it as armor. Or, more commonly, a coconut shell (hence the name).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Body Length: 16 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;inches&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Weight: 9 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;pounds&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imageslobster.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;lobster&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;That&amp;#39;s right, the largest creature with an exoskeleton is dinner for two. (Wikimedia Commons; GNU Free Document License)But to find the true monsters of the crustaceous world, we must look to the oceans. The heaviest animal with an exoskeleton is the dreaded, the mighty, the rare: the American lobster.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Length: 3.5 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;feet&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Weight: 44.4 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;pounds&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Comparable in size to: The family dog&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But that&amp;#39;s just by weight. What about by arm span?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesspider-crab.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Japanese spider crab&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Okay, this one&amp;#39;s legitimately terrifying. Although, they are reportedly &amp;quot;gentle&amp;quot; (Wikimedia Commons; GNU Free Document License)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Japanese spider crabs live in the ocean off Japan in water depths anywhere from a couple hundred feet to a couple thousand feet. They feed on shellfish and fish carcasses, and can live for a hundred years.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Leg span: 12 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;feet&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Weight: 41 &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;pounds&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Comparable in size to: The family dog after being on a medieval torture rack.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Why don&amp;#39;t creatures with exoskeletons get very large?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This comes back to the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2012/biology/macrobiology/physiology/plausible-giant-creatures/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;square-cube law discussed last week&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, with a primary focus on exoskeletal joints. How load-bearing joints (like knees and hips) in large creatures work is by distributing the load across as large an area as possible, and by cushioning and lubricating the joint by surrounding it with living tissue.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Obviously, creatures with exoskeletons can&amp;#39;t surround a joint with living tissue or they wouldn&amp;#39;t have an exoskeleton. And without that cushion and lubrication, they&amp;#39;re somewhat limited in the types of joints they can have. For instance, humans have hinge joints (elbow), ball-and-socket joints (thigh to pelvis), gliding joints (wrist), and a few others. Creatures with exoskeletons have, primarily, the pin joint.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The pin joint, essentially, has a pair of protuberances on one limb of the joint fit into a pair of depressions on the other limb of the joint. You can readily see this the next time you&amp;#39;re eating lobster if you closely examine where the &amp;quot;thumb&amp;quot; of the claw connects to the &amp;quot;hand&amp;quot; of the claw.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Pin joints are a problem as creatures increase in size because they place all the force of the joint into a relatively small area. I want you to stand up, right now, and stand on the balls of your feet with your heels off the ground. Then, with your back straight, slowly squat. Feel the pressure in your knees? Imagine that times thirty and you&amp;#39;ll have an idea what exoskeletal joints would have to resist at your size.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And we haven&amp;#39;t even gotten into the relative strength of exoskeleton vs. internal bones, cardio-respiratory efficiency, or repairability of exoskeletons vs. soft tissue and muscle.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;How do I make realistic large creatures with exoskeletons?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Do what the animals did: cheat, and don&amp;#39;t have a true exoskeleton.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagestortoise.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;tortoise&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Wikimedia Commons; GNU Free Document LicenseThe Galápagos tortoise is the largest living land tortoise; it weighs 880 pounds and is 6 feet long--you could ride one of these things (slowly). The largest living sea turtle is the leatherback; it weighs 2,000 pounds and is 10 feet long. The stupendemys, an extinct freshwater turtle, grew to 11 feet and 4,000-5,000 pounds.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Turtles and tortoises can get away with this because they don&amp;#39;t really have an exoskeleton. In particular, all their joints are encased in meaty flesh, thus avoiding the pin joint problem plaguing large crustaceans. And, while many turtles/tortoises do coat their shells in skin, there&amp;#39;s still plenty of bony shell to repel attacks.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But turtles and tortoises are the boring and the small among creatures with fake exoskeletons, even if they are a little interesting because they pulled their shoulder blades inside their rib cages.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesankylosaurus.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ankylosaurus&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;The mighty ankylosaurus&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The ankylosaurus lived during the Cretaceous period. It grew to 30 feet long and 13,000 pounds. The ankylosaurus was armored with plates of bone overlaid with keratin (the same material as your fingernails). And if that wasn&amp;#39;t enough, their tail boasted a large bony club that, when swung, could break the bones of any attackers.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Exoskeletons are for wimps. You want armor? You want size? Go with bony plates on top of muscle.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Weird Science: Visual Neglect</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/weird-science-visual-neglect.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/weird-science-visual-neglect.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesvis-neglect.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Visual neglect&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;(Every so often we talk about something really weird in science. See the complete series at &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/category/weird-science/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Weird Science&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.)&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Imagine if you were blind to everything on your left side. Not blind in your left eye--both of your eyes work fine--but you can&amp;#39;t see anything left of in front of you. When presented with the drawing of a cat and asked to reproduce it, you&amp;#39;ll draw half a cat (like in the image above).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This condition is called visual neglect, and it can happen because of the strange way we process visual information.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesvisual-pathway-231x300.gif&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Visual pathway&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Pathway of visual informationIn the image on the left, you can see the basic pathway for visual information. What you see on the left (blue) is routed to the right hemisphere, and what you see on the right (red) is routed to the left hemisphere, &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;regardless of which eye it comes from&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;. This division continues as the information is processed by the visual cortex (occipital lobe) and sent on to your brain&amp;#39;s sensory processing areas.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The parietal lobe integrates various sensory information and decides what information you focus your attention on. For instance, a blank wall isn&amp;#39;t very interesting, so the parietal lobe will push you to focus on the picture hanging in the middle of the wall. Bushes usually aren&amp;#39;t very interesting, but it is vitally important to see that leopard stalking through them.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesrightparietal.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Right parietal&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;The yellow region is the parietal lobe&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;If the right parietal lobe is damaged, sometimes the information for the left visual field is processed, but then ignored by the broken parietal lobe. This results in an inability to perceive anything in the left visual field.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Wait, it gets weirder&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;It turns out that the brain splits visual information more than just right and left. Feature Integration Theory explains how the brain splits visual information of objects into different pieces (color, shape, orientation, motion, depth, etc.; I won&amp;#39;t go very far into Feature Integration Theory, but &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feature_integration_theory&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Wikipedia is a good place to find references for it&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;) before reintegrating them into mental models. Damage in the right parietal lobe can disrupt this process, and make it impossible for people to see the left side of any and every object.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesobject_centered_neglect-220x300.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Visual object neglect&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;A patient with visual object neglect tries to draw a yard, and tries to circle all of the closed circles.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;You can see in the picture to the left the problems people with visual object neglect have. Despite being able to see a complete field of view, they are unable to perceive the left half of any individual object. The question everyone asks at this point is, &amp;quot;So, what &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;do&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; they see?&amp;quot; Unfortunately, there&amp;#39;s not a very good answer to that. They aren&amp;#39;t able to see &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;through&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; objects, obviously, and they aren&amp;#39;t freaked out that everyone only has half of a face (despite only seeing half of everyone&amp;#39;s face--including their own). The best analogy I&amp;#39;ve heard is that it&amp;#39;s like thinking about what you can see directly behind your head; you just can&amp;#39;t. &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;(If your mind has just been blown, and you think it might be your parietal lobe that has been damaged, please &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/ask-me-your-science-questions/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;contact me immediately&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. Neuroscientists want to talk to you.)&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;You keep saying &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; parietal lobe and &amp;quot;left&amp;quot; visual field--what happens when the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;left&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; parietal lobe is damaged?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Most of the data for visual neglect (and visual object neglect) comes from right-handed people, because the neurophysiology of right-handed people is best understood (because there are more of them to study). Left-handed people have different neurophysiology, and due to the rarity of visual neglect, are not often the subject of study.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;With that in mind, right-handed males (typically) use the left parietal lobe for language processing, so it&amp;#39;s difficult to find out if they are having visual neglect on their right side when their left parietal is damaged; they have problems speaking/writing and understanding spoken/written language.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Left-handed people tend to distribute their language processing across both parietal lobes, but I am not aware of any studies of parietal lobe damage to a left-handed person, so I don&amp;#39;t know what effect that has (if any) on visual neglect or language processing following parietal lobe damage.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>How to make plausible giant creatures</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/plausible-giant-creatures.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/plausible-giant-creatures.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesattack-50-foot-woman.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Attack of the 50 FT. Woman&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;If she&amp;#39;s only 50 feet tall, that car&amp;#39;s only 5 feet long. Just sayin&amp;#39;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This is a particularly... &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;apparent&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;... problem for fantasy writers. Dragons. Giant spiders. Giant bugs. Giant crabs. Giants. Tarrasques. And nearly all of them fall before the might of the Square-Cube Law.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The Square-Cube Law?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The Square-Cube law is a simple principle that states that as an object increases in size, it&amp;#39;s surface area is the cube of the size increase, while its volume is the cube of the multiplier.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Basically, as something increases in size, it&amp;#39;s volume (and, therefore, mass) increase a lot more than its surface area.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;What does the Square-Cube Law have to do with my awesome giant ants?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The Square-Cube Law applied to animals states that, as an animal is scaled up in size, it&amp;#39;s muscular cross-section is squared, but it&amp;#39;s mass is cubed.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;For instance, I&amp;#39;m 6 feet tall. If my height doubled to 12 feet and I retained my proportions, I&amp;#39;d have 4-times the muscle! Sounds great! I could lift a thousand pounds!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But I&amp;#39;d weigh 1,200 pounds.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;If I went the 50-foot person route (or, rather, 48-foot to make the math easy), I&amp;#39;d have 36-times the muscle! I could lift 9,000 pounds! Yeah!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But I&amp;#39;d weigh a whopping 43,000 pounds. I wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to lift my own arms. I wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;breathe&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. If you ever play a fantasy RPG with a hyper-realistic game master, cast an &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Enlarge&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; or &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Growth&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; spell on your enemies and argue for an insta-kill.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Okay, truly gargantuan animals are out, but elephants are big. Why can&amp;#39;t my fire-breathing giant ants be the size of an elephant?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;blockquote&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The most obvious differences between different animals are differences of size, but for some reason the zoologists have paid singularly little attention to them. In a large textbook of zoology before me I find no indication that the eagle is larger than the sparrow, or the hippopotamus bigger than the hare, though some grudging admissions are made in the case of the mouse and the whale. But yet it is easy to show that a hare could not be as large as a hippopotamus or a whale as small as a herring. For every type of animal there is a most convenient size, and a large change in size inevitably carries with it a change of form.&amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;-- &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.physlink.com/Education/essay_haldane.cfm&amp;quot;&amp;gt;On Being the Right Size by J. B. S. Haldane, 1926&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Simply put, large animals are not built like small animals, and small animals are not built like large animals. A large animal built like a small animal (say, a mouse the size of a rhino) would shatter its legs with every step.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A small animal built like a large animal would run comically slow, and either starve (if a carnivore) or be eaten (if an herbivore). You can directly see this by looking at animals that have been bred to be small--if you put a teacup pig up against a wild boar, the teacup pig&amp;#39;s going to have problems surviving.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesteacup-v-boar.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Teacup pig vs. Boar&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Left: Full-grown &amp;quot;teacup&amp;quot; pig, twice the size of a chicken (Geoff Robinson Photography). Right: Wild boar, larger than a great dane (Wikimedia Commons). And... fight!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;I suppose this means my fire-breathing, intelligent giant ants can&amp;#39;t fly.&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Nope. And neither can dragons (&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0061020648/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0061020648&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Terry Pratchett&amp;#39;s Guards! Guards!&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thunwe-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=0061020648&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ir_t_thunwe-20_l_as2_o_1_a_0061020648&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; is an excellent, hilarious criticism of dragons in novel form). The problem with giant flying creatures is, once again, wingspan and muscle cross-sections. If an elephant wanted to fly, it would need fifty-foot wings. But if an elephant had fifty-foot wings, the wings would break under their own weight just unfolding.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Airplanes fly!&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Airplanes have rigid wings made from titanium (and other ultra-strong materials) and jet engines.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Blimps can fly!&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Blimps are giant, bloated things filled with hydrogen or helium.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Helicopters can fly!&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;...you&amp;#39;re not even trying anymore, self-alter-ego, are you?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Nobody cares! They just want intelligent, flying, fire-breathing, giant ants!&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Most people probably don&amp;#39;t care that much. But some people roll their eyes at every unexplained &amp;quot;giant {insert animal}&amp;quot;. And, at the end of the day, shouldn&amp;#39;t we be promoting solid science as far as we can?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Anyway, giant {animal} has been played out; it&amp;#39;s been done. Wouldn&amp;#39;t it be better to be creating new creatures that, while similar to other creatures, are actually built like they should be?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Fine. I can&amp;#39;t make my intelligent, thirty-legged, flying, fire-breathing, elephant-sized ants. What giant things &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;can&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; I make?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;All kinds! With an awareness of physiology, you can build giant creatures like giant creatures are really built.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Large land animals have tree trunk-like legs like an elephant, or a compressed body with stretched, oblique legs like a giraffe. The death knell for large land animals is legs that jut from the side of the body (like a crocodile or spider); what they need are legs directly under the body (like humans, rhinos, and the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://speculativeevolution.wikia.com/wiki/Megasquid&amp;quot;&amp;gt;megasquid&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, although the megasquid has other problems).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Flying winged animals can&amp;#39;t get very large (at least, on an Earth-like planet). The largest flying bird was &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentavis_magnificens&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Argentavis magnificens&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, which weighed a mere 180 pounds.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Blimps are huge, and can certainly fly. But, as previously stated, they&amp;#39;re giant and bloated, so saying an ant is flying because it&amp;#39;s abdomen is filled with hydrogen is silly at best. But a giant flying puffer fish-like creature filled with hydrogen is more believable. Plus, when the plot inevitably calls for one to explode, all the spines will fly out and hit everyone you don&amp;#39;t like.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There&amp;#39;s also life cycles! Your giant winged bird could fly as a youth, but as it matures the wings stop growing, and the legs become thicker and stronger. It won&amp;#39;t be able to fly anymore, but it could step on cheetahs.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When Brandon Sanderson wanted giant crustaceans in &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765365278/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0765365278&amp;quot;&amp;gt;The Way of Kings&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thunwe-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=0765365278&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ir_t_thunwe-20_l_as2_o_1_a_0765365278&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;, he looked at what he would have to do to the world to make that happen (tidal forces, gravity, atmospheric density, etc.).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Mobile plants are big right now (a concept to tackle on a different day), and the largest known organism is a grove of aspen trees with an interconnected root system--it may look like a forest, but they&amp;#39;re all one plant. Make them semi-mobile, with a bit of intelligence, and you&amp;#39;ve suddenly got 100 acres of hostile forest controlled by a single mind.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesblue-whale.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Blue whale&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;The ocean places few limits on animal size. (Wikimedia Commons)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Even the ocean, ultimately, has limits. The blue whale is only 110 feet long, and it&amp;#39;s the largest animal to ever have lived. Some of this might be food related (a blue whale can eat over 7,000 pounds of food in a day). But a lot of it is probably respiratory and circulatory: blue whales need a lot of oxygen to move to an enormous number of cells and, as we know from the square-cube law, that gets harder and harder as the creature gets bigger and bigger. Without a more efficient alternative to oxygen respiration, I doubt any creature could become larger than a blue whale.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;But what if I want to do something &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;really&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; weird?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;For most genres, Rule of Cool trumps absolute realism. For instance, on the Excustoria wiki someone wanted &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://excustoria.wikia.com/wiki/Giant_Spider&amp;quot;&amp;gt;two mile-long spiders&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. So we put the spiders in the ocean and gave them symbiotic moss that handled the respiration for them, a &amp;quot;titanium alloy&amp;quot; exoskeleton for strength, and a permanently-filled swim bladder for flotation. The spiders move slowly to conserve energy, and primarily float along the coast filtering sea water.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This still ultimately fails, since the moss wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to respirate enough for them, and they&amp;#39;d have severe problems with pumping fluids and moving at all (especial since spiders move by hydraulics, not muscles), but it&amp;#39;s better than, &amp;quot;They just exist, okay?&amp;quot;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When designing new animals, it&amp;#39;s often useful to start at &amp;quot;cool new animal,&amp;quot; then figure out a way to make it happen. Often, that process will take you to a far better place (generic giant spider to &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;floating titanium spider island&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;), and could even change the entire face of your fantasy world into a more complex, interesting place.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;(For anyone creating new creatures, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.physlink.com/Education/essay_haldane.cfm&amp;quot;&amp;gt;On Being the Right Size by J. B. S. Haldane&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; is essential reading.)&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Etymology: Matinée</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/etymology-matinee.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/etymology-matinee.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Matinée is a rather interesting word, in that in English it refers to a movie or theater showing during midday/early afternoon, while the French word it originates from (matinée) literally means, &amp;quot;Of the morning&amp;quot; (from the Latin mātūtīnus) and referred to showings in the morning.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;So what happened?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;When you were growing up, was the midday meal called dinner, or lunch? And the evening meal dinner, or supper, or either?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Convention stated that a matinée occurred before dinner (the midday meal at the time). Rich people--the people who could, in the mid 19th century, afford to go to the theater--began to sleep in as a method of showing their wealth (&amp;quot;Wake up at dawn? What am I, a farmer? HA HA HA I&amp;#39;m hilarious.&amp;quot;) This slowly pushed &amp;quot;dinner&amp;quot; later into the day, until the wealthy were waking up around noon, and eating &amp;quot;dinner&amp;quot; around 5 pm. This forced theaters to push their matinées into the early afternoon to accommodate their late-rising patrons. As theater became cheaper, particularly with the rise of film, theaters kept their &amp;quot;matinées&amp;quot; in the early afternoon since the term had stuck, just as &amp;quot;dinner&amp;quot; became, for many people, the evening meal.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Incredible Impossible Hulk</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/the-impossible-hulk.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/the-impossible-hulk.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imageshulk.jpeg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Hulk&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I have an irrational dislike for the Hulk. I admit it&amp;#39;s irrational. The Avengers (in the latest movie incarnation) include: a guy in a flying metal shell with an impossible power source; a magic demigod; and a guy who&amp;#39;s essentially on the biggest adrenaline high of anyone&amp;#39;s life at all times (with a magic-material shield). And I&amp;#39;m okay with all of them.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But the Hulk... &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;bothers&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; me. And it comes down to his size, or, more precisely, his mass.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The Law of Conservation of Mass states (in the simplified version) that matter can never be created or destroyed, merely moved and transformed. This, unfortunately, puts the Hulk in a rather awkward position, because he obviously gains mass transforming from Bruce Banner into the Hulk.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imageshulk-crush-table.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Hulk crushing a surgical table&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;The Hulk crushes a surgical table by gaining mass.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;So where does the mass come from? Let&amp;#39;s look at the options.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Surrounding matter?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;I&amp;#39;ve never seen the Hulk eat or drink anything while transforming, or vomit while transforming back into Banner. Which means he&amp;#39;d have to be inhaling 200+ pounds of air and converting that into muscle and bone (somehow). At sea level, that&amp;#39;s about 6 cubic yards of air. If he was inhaling 200 pounds of air, everyone near him would feel a strong wind as air rushes into the lungs of the mighty Hulk.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Since there&amp;#39;s no wind, that&amp;#39;s not where his mass comes from.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Energy turned into matter?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Ah, yes, Einstein&amp;#39;s good old E=mc2. The problem with this idea is that c2 is the speed of light (and light is &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;really&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; fast) &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;squared&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;. Basically, a small amount of matter can be turned into an enormous amount of energy, but if you want to go the other way--energy to matter--you need an absurd amount of energy.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;How much energy? 8.089 * 1018 Joules. I wanted to see how large of a nuclear explosion that is, but &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=nuclear+explosion&amp;amp;a=*C.nuclear+explosion-_*Formula.dflt-&amp;amp;f2=1933+megaton+of+TNT&amp;amp;x=0&amp;amp;y=0&amp;amp;f=NuclearWeaponEffects.Y_1933+megaton+of+TNT&amp;quot;&amp;gt;WolframAlpha doesn&amp;#39;t calculate explosions that large&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. It&amp;#39;s more than half of all the energy the United States produced in 2001. It&amp;#39;s more than &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;all&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; the energy from the Sun that hits the &amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;entire&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt; Earth in 30 seconds.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This is all assuming perfect energy-to-mass conversion. No systems have 100% efficiency, though, so we&amp;#39;re probably looking at 1.5 times that much energy, and half of it dissipates as waste. And by, &amp;quot;dissipates,&amp;quot; I mean, &amp;quot;roasts everyone nearby alive because that&amp;#39;s still too much energy for WolframAlpha to calculate the size of an equivalent nuclear explosion.&amp;quot;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And that&amp;#39;s every single time he turns into the Hulk!&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But that&amp;#39;s not even the worst part! When he turns back into Banner, all of that mass gets turned back into energy, and the resulting explosion catches the atmosphere on fire and kills all life as we know it.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Every. Single. Time.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;So where does the mass come from?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Magical plot holes. Which is disappointing, since the Hulk has been one of the &amp;quot;science&amp;quot; superheroes (which are few to begin with), but they can&amp;#39;t come up with an explanation better than &amp;quot;gamma magic&amp;quot;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;How could we get a superhero with Hulk powers?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The tesseract from the recent Avengers movie actually provides a suitable pseudoscience explanation--especially since they&amp;#39;ve linked the tesseract to gamma radiation. If Banner/Hulk had a tesseract-like device inside him--perhaps distributed through his bones--that was triggered by his anger, the tesseract device could create a small wormhole between Banner/Hulk and, say, a star, which would be able to provide suitable energy for the energy-to-mass conversion required to spontaneously gain 200+ pounds, and safely vent excess energy for the mass-to-energy powerdown. The mass is gained as super-muscle and bone due to the tesseract&amp;#39;s integration with his DNA and self-organizing powers.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Image stills from The Incredible Hulk, copyright Marvel; Fair use: critique.&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Parasitic corpse flower steals genes from its host</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/parasitic-corpse-flower-steals-genes-from-its-host.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 8 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/parasitic-corpse-flower-steals-genes-from-its-host.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagescorpse-flower.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;corpse flower&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Image from Wikimedia Commons (Creative Commons)&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Article at &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/science-sushi/2012/06/08/parasitic-flower-pirates-genes-from-its-host/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Scientific American&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Weird Science: Split-Brain</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/split-brain.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 8 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/split-brain.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagessplit-brain.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;split-brain&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;em&amp;gt;(Every so often we talk about something really weird in science. See the complete series at &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/category/weird-science/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Weird Science&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.)&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Most people are aware that their brains are split into left and right hemispheres. There&amp;#39;s a large bundle of nerves that connect the two called the corpus callosum. That&amp;#39;s right, the only thing preventing you from having two separate minds living in one skull is a single bundle of nerves.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But it gets weirder. Certain kinds of epilepsy occur because of an uncontrolled propagation of anomalous nerve signals in the brain (also known as &amp;quot;for some reason, electricity in your brain has gone crazy&amp;quot;). These types of epilepsy can often be completely cured by severing the corpus callosum, because the propagation will halt when it tries to bridge the gap between hemispheres and can&amp;#39;t.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesalien-hand.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;alien-hand&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Not that kind of alien handSometimes these people will develop things like &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alien_hand_syndrome&amp;quot;&amp;gt;alien hand syndrome&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, where the person becomes convinced that one hand (usually the left) is acting on its own, and contrary to his or her normal behavior. But usually you can meet them, befriend them, and know them for years and never know they have two minds inside one skull.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Psychologists, however, know how to test split-brain patients in very specific ways. For the most part, language is handled in the left hemisphere, which means the right hemisphere is essentially mute. Every time you have a thought in a language (&amp;quot;Hmmm... I wonder if I should...&amp;quot;), that&amp;#39;s your left hemisphere.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But if your corpus callosum is cut, that essentially means your right hemisphere doesn&amp;#39;t have a say (so to speak) in what&amp;#39;s going on, but it can still act (using the left side of the body). This puts the left hemisphere in the awkward position of verbally explaining why the right hemisphere did something, and a lot of times the left hemisphere will make a rational explanation even though, really, it has no idea what&amp;#39;s going on.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagessplit-brain-chicken-shovel.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;split-brain-chicken-shovel&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Split brain patients can choose associated images using both sides of their brains.For instance, the image on the right shows a split-brain patient choosing pictures that are associated with the pictures on the screen in front of him. The left visual field is processed by the right hemisphere, so the left hand (controlled by the right hemisphere) chooses the shovel because of the snow. The right hand chooses the chicken for the chicken foot. But when asked why the choices were made, the patient says the chicken for the chicken foot, and the shovel to clean out the chicken coop. This is because the left hemisphere controls language, but &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;can&amp;#39;t see the snowy house&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, so it just makes up a reason for the shovel.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The Conscious Mind&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And this is where most people&amp;#39;s idea of the &amp;quot;conscious mind&amp;quot; kind of falls apart. Most people consider the conscious mind the language part of the brain: I think this sentence, I am conscious of the sentence I just thought, that is my conscious mind (goes all the back to &amp;quot;I think, therefore I am&amp;quot;). But that only accounts for half (at most) of our conscious mind: the left hemisphere, and it&amp;#39;s language processing capabilities.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;A good example of this is chess masters. When a chess master is playing a match, they don&amp;#39;t process it like a computer (continue down every possible set of moves and choose the most advantageous). What they do is &amp;quot;sum up&amp;quot; the game in their mind based on games they&amp;#39;ve played, games they&amp;#39;ve seen, and games they&amp;#39;ve studied, and make a move in a way that the resulting &amp;quot;sum&amp;quot; in their mind is the greatest. This spatial summary is the kind of thing that the right hemisphere does very well, but the left hemisphere couldn&amp;#39;t do with a map (mainly because the left hemisphere is also bad with maps).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;But despite not thinking in sentences (indeed, many chess masters have difficulty explaining exactly why they make particular moves), I don&amp;#39;t think anyone will argue that the chess master wasn&amp;#39;t using their conscious mind to make the play.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;What split-brain condition is not&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The split-brain condition is not, in any way, associated with multiple personality disorder (more properly known as dissociative identity disorder). The hemispheres don&amp;#39;t take turns &amp;quot;driving&amp;quot; the body and acting as different personalities. Both hemispheres are fully operational and present at all times and &amp;quot;drive&amp;quot; the body simultaneously, the left hemisphere controlling the right of the body and the right hemisphere controlling the left of the body.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;What can I write with this?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;In most media (books, movies, television, videogames), a &amp;quot;crazy&amp;quot; character or brain damaged character acts in a very general kind of &amp;quot;crazy&amp;quot; way. This can range from catatonic and drooling, to gibbering and irrational behavior, to generalized sociopathy. But generally speaking, most people with mental disorders or brain damage have a very specific condition. A phobia. An anxiety disorder. A personality disorder (watch &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00009W5CA/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00009W5CA&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Fargo&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thunwe-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B00009W5CA&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ir_t_thunwe-20_l_as2_o_1_a_B00009W5CA&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; for a good primer on personality disorders).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Mental homogeneity is boring. If someone&amp;#39;s insane in your story, break out of the boring and get specific.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Your eyes are stupid</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/your-eyes-are-stupid.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 7 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/your-eyes-are-stupid.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dJyvcNmYwr4&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dJyvcNmYwr4&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Video by &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://ashow.zefrank.com/episodes/25&amp;quot;&amp;gt;zefrank&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>In space no one can hear you scream</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/in-space-no-one-can-hear-you-scream.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 6 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/in-space-no-one-can-hear-you-scream.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesalien-poster.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Alien&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;...but everyone can hear your lasers and explosions.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;We&amp;#39;ve all seen the space action movies. Star Wars. Star Trek. Armageddon. And, yes, even Alien, which acknowledges that no one can hear you scream, then ends with a noisy spaceship explosion.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There is no sound in space; or, more precisely, there is so little sound in space that the energy required to create an audible sound (such as a supernova) would instantly kill anyone close enough to hear it.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Why is there no sound in space?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesear-300x203.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ear&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;This is your ear. This is your ear on sound.To get into that, first we have to take a quick look into exactly what sound is. Sound is the rhythmic compression and expansion of molecules (primarily air molecules) against the ear drum (also called the tympanic membrane). The ear drum vibrates, moving some bones that jostle the fluid in the cochlea. The cochlea is full of tiny hairs that relay the pattern of jostles to your brain, which interprets them as sounds.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;So, why is there no sound in space?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;There&amp;#39;s no air in space to vibrate. There is a tiny amount of space dust, and some vague amounts of gas, but the gas isn&amp;#39;t enough for sound to move through loudly enough that humans can hear it. Unless the sound is really, really loud--even the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/3096776.stm&amp;quot;&amp;gt;black hole that hums a B-flat&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; can&amp;#39;t be heard without sensitive equipment.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Why is there sound in space in movies?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Because it seems fake without sound. &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00005ASUM/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00005ASUM&amp;quot;&amp;gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thunwe-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B00005ASUM&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ir_t_thunwe-20_l_as2_o_1_a_B00005ASUM&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; was the first movie to feature truly soundless space, and Stanley Kubrik was able to use it to unsettle the audience (and terrify the characters). When the astronauts are in space, all they can hear (and, therefore, all the audience hears) is their breathing, which adds to the feelings of isolation and paranoia that the characters are experiencing, but seems almost contrived.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And 2001 didn&amp;#39;t have to deal with space battles and explosions. If there&amp;#39;s something everyone knows, it&amp;#39;s that explosions are &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;loud&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;. We can&amp;#39;t help it; we live in a constantly audible world.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Then there&amp;#39;s the issue of history. When Edgar Rice Burroughs wrote &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0345331389/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0345331389&amp;quot;&amp;gt;A Princess of Mars&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thunwe-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=0345331389&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ir_t_thunwe-20_l_as2_o_1_a_0345331389&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; in 1917 (recently adapted into the movie &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005LAIH2W/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=thunwe-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B005LAIH2W&amp;quot;&amp;gt;John Carter&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thunwe-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B005LAIH2W&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;ir_t_thunwe-20_l_as2_o_1_a_B005LAIH2W&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;), he had no way of knowing that Mars had almost no atmosphere; he just invented a few aliens and threw John Carter at them.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Pulp science fiction continued to have sound in space because people didn&amp;#39;t know any better; we didn&amp;#39;t actually go into space until after World War II. Then, once we knew more about space, it became difficult to remove sound from fiction in space. There was a multi-generational tradition of sounds in space that people (both authors and audience) didn&amp;#39;t want to give up.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;What do I do with this?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;That largely depends on what you&amp;#39;re writing. Films and television shows will often be forced to have sounds because the executives funding the projects will require it to &amp;quot;feel real&amp;quot;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;For literature, it largely depends on the genre. Pulp science fiction typically follows the Rule of Cool before realism. Hard science fiction requires accuracy at all costs. Space opera can go either way, but usually attempts to be realistic, and glosses over inaccuracies with technobabble (such as &amp;quot;aural simulators&amp;quot; to explain sound in space).&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Is there anything else that doesn&amp;#39;t have sound that pop culture thinks does?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Lots of things, but I&amp;#39;ll leave you with just one more. Most revolvers, when you spin the cylinder, don&amp;#39;t make that clicking sound.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;And now you know.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagesrevolver.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;revolver&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Photo by SoulRider.22; CC license&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Venus will pass in front of the Sun today</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/venus-will-pass-in-front-of-the-sun-today.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 5 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/venus-will-pass-in-front-of-the-sun-today.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-nXv9YvkNyA&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-nXv9YvkNyA&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Update:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Z9rM8ChTjY&amp;quot;&amp;gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Z9rM8ChTjY&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Laws of Physics--Writing</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/06/laws-of-physics-writing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 4 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/06/laws-of-physics-writing.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;AuthorCulture has an interesting take on &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://authorculture.blogspot.com/2012/06/he-eyed-her-from-head-to-toe.html&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Newtonian physics for writers&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Moon and the Sun</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/04/the-moon-and-the-sun.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/04/the-moon-and-the-sun.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagessun-eclipses.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Eclipse&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;Photographed by Jon Sullivan; public domain&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;This is for &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.theoatmeal.com/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Matthew Inman&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, who wanted to know why the Sun and Moon appear to be roughly equal sizes.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The simple answer (which you probably already know)&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The Sun is really big, but it&amp;#39;s also really far away. The Moon, while much smaller, is much closer.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;The math answer&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The size something appears to be relative to the viewer is called its &amp;quot;visual angle&amp;quot;. A visual angle can be calculated using the equation V=2arctan(S/2D) where V is the visual angle, S is the linear size of the object, and D is the distance between the observer and the object.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/2012/04/pinhole2.jpg&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;http://azuaron.github.io/imagespinhole2.jpg&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;visual angle&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The Moon averages about 384,405 km from the Earth, and has a diameter (linear size) of about 3,474 km. V=2arctan(3474/(2*384405)) = .0090378 degrees&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;The Sun averages about 150 million km from the Earth, and has a diameter of about 1,392,000km. V=2arctan(1392000/(2*150000000)) = .0092799 degrees&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;While close, the Sun averages slightly larger than the moon (2 millionths of a degree of visual angle), which is (one of the reasons) why the Sun is not completely obscured by the Moon during an eclipse.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;But why do they appear to be the &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;same&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt; size?&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Coincidence. Earth just happens to be just far enough away from the Sun, which just happens to be just the right size to appear to be the same size as the Moon, which just happens to be the right distance from Earth and just the right size.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Or God&amp;#39;s laughing at us.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>World Building: Excustoria</title>
      <link>http://azuaron.github.io/2012/01/world-building-excustoria.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2012/01/world-building-excustoria.html</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;If you&amp;#39;re not familiar with &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.writingexcuses.com/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Writing Excuses&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, become familiar. If you are, go listen to the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.writingexcuses.com/2012/01/15/writing-excuses-7-3-fauna-and-flora/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;episode concerning Fauna and Flora&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. You&amp;#39;ll probably want to familiarize yourself with the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://www.writingexcuses.com/2011/12/04/writing-excuses-6-27-fantasy-setting-yard-sale/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;magic system&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; as well, if you haven&amp;#39;t already.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Then join us at the &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://excustoria.wikia.com/wiki/Excustoria_Wiki&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Excustoria wiki&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; for building the coastal ecology.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</description>	  
    </item>

  </channel> 
</rss>
